coming to the frontier research session.
My name is Igor Babushkin. Um, formerly
I was a co-founder of XAI. Now I'm the
CEO of a new AI company called RAI. I'm
going to be moderating the session.
We've got some really amazing speakers
for you today. Very excited to to get
started with the talks. Um, before we
get started, just wanted to kind of set
the scene a little bit. Um, so this year
we've seen some incredible progress in
terms of agentic AI, especially around
coding agents. So they've really taken
the world by storm. A lot of the
software engineers I know, they swear by
them. They tell me, I haven't written a
line of code in six months. Um, and it's
still, you know, still spreading across
the world. There's also a lot of
economic impact with companies
generating tremendous amounts of revenue
from serving these powerful coding
agents. Um and it really know as a
researcher it really kind of creates
this question what will come next as are
coding agents the end pro probably not
there going to be some new developments
even more capable agents um and it's
know there are multiple possible
directions we're going to be exploring a
few of these today with our speakers um
so for the first uh presentation uh
we've got Richard so um who's going to
talk about his new air company recursive
super intelligence so to give you a
little bit of introduction Richard is
somebody that I'm sure many of you are
familiar with. Um he's widely credited
with pioneering the use of neuronet
networks in lang language learning in
general um including the use of word
vectors, contextual vectors, maybe
you've heard of recursive neonets um as
well. Um and he's one of the highest
cited researchers in NLP today. He's
also a very very prolific entrepreneur
having founded Metammind then you.com
and now he's come out of stealth with
his latest uh startup recursive super
intelligence. He's raised $650 million
to build AI that masters research and
ultimately is capable of improving
itself further and further. So, welcome
Richard Sure.
[applause]
>> Hello. Hello. Really excited to be here
in Berkeley and yeah, we'll talk to you
a little bit today about what I feel
like is my personal version of going to
Mars. Um, and that is the Eureka
machine. It's uh the ultimate invention
for humanity to automate all future
inventions. Uh and to get there uh and
to motivate that um I'll I think we have
to get to recursive self-improving super
intelligence to along the way. Now, one
of the processes we're the most inspired
by which is still to some degree
underexplored in the AI community
broadly is that of open-ended evolution.
uh and we'll walk in a very quick
succession from billions of years of
biology to thousands of years of science
uh to you know the now weeksl long
craziness uh that is AI if we start with
uh biological evolution we can see that
uh it is one of the most inspiring sort
of open-ended processes uh that we're
aware of and indeed when you zoom in you
realize that only at the very end of
this very very long billion plus year
process. Uh it led to us right inventing
our eyes and and so on developing those
uh and so we want to basically be able
to replicate this but with technology
and if you think about technological
evolution um it also was one of the
major contributing factors to allowing
humanity to thrive um not just in terms
of GDP but also just in terms of
sustaining and allowing people to
flourish on this planet. And it mostly
came again from technology, basic things
like hunting and farming to
enlightenment, the industrial revolution
and so on. Now let's zoom into just the
last uh few hundred years and maybe a
few thousand years. Even there uh there
has been this incredible move uh that
allowed more people to live on this
planet because of of technology. And
what's interesting is that when you zoom
out and you think about this, I believe
actually that the only perpetual source
of growth is technology as uh Mark Andre
said uh and in fact we can go even
further and say that there are no
material problems that are not cannot be
solved with even more technology
material not psychological problems and
you know political and so on. It's a
different beast. Um, but I believe that
uh we need to be able to really
accelerate this and not doing it is
actually a bigger danger uh to not
allowing as many people to flourish. And
what's really exciting is that um in
many ways our generation was too late to
explore the earth uh too early to
explore the stars but we're right on
time to build super intelligence. uh and
unlike previous technological jumps uh
this will actually happen I think a lot
faster because uh of technologies like
recursive self-improving super
intelligence and when you look at some
examples of of technologies that have
moved very quickly you can actually see
that within one lifetime like in early
1903 or so uh no human had ever
sustained powered flight and 60 years
later we landed on the moon right so
within 60 years within one lifetime
uh humanity had this massive jump and
now a lot of uh acceleration technology
is in software so it's even faster and
so I think our generation will go from
no human having been able to interact
with an intelligence an artificial
intelligence that's smarter than it to
one that is likely smarter on almost
every task uh than a human. I think
that's that's the goal here. And uh in
the interest of time I'll kind of switch
uh or or move through these fairly
quickly. But you know when you think
about technology there's obviously deep
theories and connections to to science
um and and theory of it and we think
about science. But long story short we
basically can fairly clearly say that
more science will lead to more
technology which will lead to more
growth which will lead to more human
flourishing. And that then begs the
question well how do we accelerate
scientific discovery? That is uh the
number one goal uh for us. Uh and
there's a lot of there a lot of good
reasons of why we should do it um uh to
mostly help um with uh help humanity
solve a lot of different problems. Now
this is something I've been thinking
about for quite some time. I just
finished a book. It'll come out in
September called the Eureka Machine. Um
and uh I I believe that AI is the actual
unlock for this. Uh and when you think
about this full Eureka machine in all of
its glory, there will be basically four
different pillars. uh those pillars are
first the existing knowledge that we
have with humanity mostly now
incorporated by uh LMS. A lot of people
struggle sometimes with sort of legality
and the copyrights and you know
companies infusing all the knowledge
from the web into an LM but now that
they're open source they're becoming
more and more a resource for humanity
just like the internet had been. So I
think that is the first pillar existing
knowledge that's publicly available. The
second pillar is going to have to be uh
grounding it in a lot of scientific
measurement data. Uh because human eyes
are very limited. Uh human senses are
very limited. Obviously I in terms of
the upper bound of perceptual
intelligence could be much much bigger
and that is unlocked largely through
scientific measurements. Now not
everything uh has been measured uh and
hence we need a third pillar which will
be simulations. Everything you can
simulate, anything you can uh
essentially verify, AI will obviously
solve. Like I personally have never been
that surprised that we can beat chess
and go and all these other games because
you can essentially simulate it, verify
it and hence create unlimited amounts of
training data. And then of course there
will be some things that we cannot yet
simulate either and we eventually have
to go and actually do robotic uh process
automation and really automate uh
physical uh labs. And then on top of
these four pillars, uh you essentially
have um an agent swarm. And that is what
uh that agent swarm ideally before you
ask it to do physical experiments and so
on, you want to have it have the
equivalent of like 5,000 different PhDs.
And so that is uh essentially uh our
goal at recursive uh where we want to
automate uh science uh and which better
science to start than the science of AI
itself, right? And that's where you get
uh recursive self-improvement where in a
very scientific way uh you essentially
allow the eye to build a certain sense
of self-awareness of its own
shortcomings based on you know the
entire process uh from pre-training uh
to harnesses and everything in between
and I think that is now uniquely
possible especially actually this year
because AI is code and AI can't code
right and so now that we have been able
to accomplish that and accomplish it
also for longer and longer time horizons
that allows us to really like let AI
work on itself. And uh when you think
about the process of science but also AI
research, it's essentially three major
steps. It's the ideation,
implementation, and validation of ideas.
And then it just is now the question,
how well can you ideulate? How many
novel truly novel ideas can you come up
with? uh obviously now we can implement
them better and better uh and uh I think
the validation still can take a lot of
time and uh one thing that we're seeing
in a lot of different places now is auto
research which is an incredibly useful
milestone a stepping stone towards true
recursive self-improvement where you
like ask one AI to improve some other
system right that's not true recursive
self-improvement it's just auto research
uh but when we took our RSI system and
actually applied it to three different
benchmarks that thousands of people have
worked on often together with their
agents um and their own like sort of
human curiosity. Uh we could see that
this AI actually outperformed years of
prior research um across three different
benchmarks. one it's called nano chat uh
very popular auto research uh benchmark
where we're we're able to reduce the
bits per bite uh significantly within
less than two days of like asking our
system to research this problem. NanoGPD
speedrun is also very useful trying to
create uh faster and faster um training
algorithms and then soul execbench uh is
a benchmark from Nvidia that basically
uh evaluates kernels CUDA kernels the
interface between GPUs and and actual AI
code uh and there too we made uh
significant jump and it's interesting
because it's not just like tuning
hyperparameters it makes some truly
useful inventions like incorporating
hash tables into transformers and other
things like coming up with new types of
momentum and so on and uh you know speed
is very important. If you want to reduce
the intelligence per dollar uh of your
foundational models then you know that
becomes crucial and uh CUDA kernels are
a big part uh of uh all of these uh
types of of algorithms and then running
them efficiently in in very large data
centers. And you can imagine that if you
spend billions and billions of dollars
on these data centers and then you could
improve them by five or 10% efficiency,
it's a very significant um you know end
result uh for companies. And so as we
look into the arc I think of human
history uh and it sounds a little bit
grandiose but I do really believe that
that we're living like in this moment in
time right now. uh then uh I think
recursive self-improving super
intelligence that automates this kind of
uh um scientific discovery is another
step function in a sequence of of these
uh cumulative scurves and in many ways
we have only started scratching the
surface in AI. Um I actually tried to
define AI in its uh full sort of um
complexity and there is no really good
definition. Um I think ultimately it
boils down to three principal components
uh which is essentially prediction uh
which is mathematically equivalent to
compression multiplied with actions
multiplied with goals. And from these
three principal components you can
eventually essentially evaluate uh these
and and uh study these 10 different
spaces of intelligence. And just to give
you a sense of how far away we are uh
and then I'll I'll end the talk. Um the
visual intelligence which is the
simplest one to sort of uh think through
is incredibly early. Right? We often
think in computer vision in terms of
just the electromagnetic frequency
spectrum of the human eyes. Human eyes
are not that amazing, right? Mantis
shrimp have more amazing eyes. Um but uh
you could if you think about the upper
bounds of intelligence and how far how
much further AI can go, you can realize
that it couldn't just be binocular
vision. You can have millions and
trillions of sensors. Eventually, you
can think about the speed of light cone
around all of these sensors and how far
apart they could be to still be able to
communicate to one central intelligence.
And you can realize that they can see
all the way down to the quantum level of
uncertainty there. And that's an upper
bound. And you they can go all the way
up to um gravitational waves and then
merge all of that. think through many
more different uh layers of abstractions
of types of objects and so on. So just
to give you a sense like when people
think oh AI is going to not go that much
further we're literally astronomically
far away from the upper bounds across
many of the different spaces of
intelligence and that I think makes it
very exciting and still a very useful
area to research. So yeah if you want to
work on those kinds of things uh let us
know. Thank you. [applause]
Should I sit here or go back?
>> Thank you, Richard. Next up, we have Ed
Chi, who's the VP of research, was VP of
research at Google DeepMind, where he
leads machine learning research on LLM
applications such as Lambda. He was
involved in the launch of Bard and
Gemini, and now he's working on
universal assistant agents like Project
Astra. He's a co-author of the famous
chain of thought prompting work which
today is one of the core ideas that
power all of these amazing agents that
we're using every day. Um before Google
he was a principal scientist at Xerox
Spark and he's an ACM fellow and a
member of the sik chi academy. A few
people have shipped agents to more users
than ad. So please welcome Etchie.
All right. Uh hi everyone. Uh good
afternoon. Um last night I was at the
reception and someone told me that based
upon last year's talk uh they made a lot
of money in the stock market. Um so I
don't know if I can make that promise
today but uh to be honest I have a
confession to make. I'm actually a very
slow uh learner. Um and I've always felt
like I have an imposttor syndrome. How
many of you have imposttor syndrome?
Yeah, me too. So, you know, one of the
things I wanted to talk about is that um
it took me a long time to figure out
what were really the key ideas that
really matter because as a scientist,
all I really cared about was not writing
the next paper, but what actually what
the next big idea is and in reality,
even though I published more than 200
papers, there's only probably 10 that I
feel like I'm even proud of. And um so I
wanted to tell you in retrospect what I
feel like are three very important ideas
from the first two decades of my
graduate research career. Um and they
come from the area of information
retrieval. And these are ideas that many
of you have already heard about. So I'm
not going to go them into detail
obviously. But the first one, let's just
pause and think about the first great
invention of humankind in my opinion,
which was the library. And the library
actually is built upon the idea of
indexing. And so that was the very first
big idea from the 90s where we used map
reduce to build very large search
engines. But it needed a second idea
which was vector space models. And only
a few years ago um the wordtovec paper
was voted as the um 10th year uh test of
time award for word tovec and it was
based upon the idea of vector space
models using neural networks to compute
relationship between words so that we
could have better understanding of
semantics and what words really mean and
those were already two ideas and I'm
going to tell you the first major
mistake I made as a slow thinker and a
low learner. In 1992, my uh PhD adviser
John Rele came to me and said, "What if
we use those vector space models and
applied them to user item matrices
instead of document turn matrices? This
was the birth of recommendation systems
and I told him it was a dumb idea."
Okay. And the reality was that once we
got huge supercomputers, we were able to
do one thing much much better as a
result that made search and
recommendation system so much better and
that was sorting. The reality is that
what we're doing is ranking, right? So
if you think about the fact that next
token prediction is nothing but sorting
to the next most likely word you're
going to say or to communicate
everything has been about sorting. So
the third idea from the period the l
latter part of 20110 to 2015 is deep
neural networks and at Google um
actually we made very good use of this
as you can imagine but in 1992 when I
was a graduate student this was a
supercomput.
G flops of computation
the phone in my pocket right now has
1,690 gigaflops. Okay, almost a thousand
times more computation and all this
powers all the applications that's in
your pocket right now. We're all walking
around with like a thousand
supercomputers in our pocket. Luckily,
it's not burning a hole in your pocket,
right? Um, and so if you think about the
whole internet ecosystem, this is what
we're talking about. This is the whole
thing is still based upon sorting and
ranking and recommendation systems and
search. So those were the three ideas
from the first two decades of my
research career. In my opinion that
really matters indexing, vector space
models and deep learning. Now the it's
the interesting thing is that deep
learning is the real thing that
connected to our present time.
There were three ideas from 2015 to 2025
and I noticed Vincent is here and you'll
hopefully agree with me that really
mattered from those 10 years of uh time
period. How many of you have seen this
figure? Yeah, everyone has seen them.
Have you ever read it the paper?
Okay. The very first sentence of the
abstract says this. The dominant
sequence transduction models are based
upon complex recurrent neural networks
that include an encoder and decoder.
I'll admit to you that the first time I
read this paper, I have no clue what
that meant. How many of you still don't
know what that means? Yeah, that's what
I thought. Almost at least 50% of the
people raised their hand. What is
sequential transduction? What the f does
that even mean? Right? It turns out that
the word transduction means the
transformation from one energy wave into
another energy wave. As an example,
you're experiencing transduction right
now. A microphone that I'm wearing right
now is a transducer that transmits
transforms soundwave into electrical
wave. And there are speakers around this
hall that turns those electrical waves
back into sound. That's how you're able
to hear me. In fact, your ear is a
transducer. It's listening to what I'm
saying. And that sound is going into
your ear which has a mindbrain. And that
membrane is vibrating and it's connected
to a neuron. And that those neurons are
transmitting information into your
brain. That's how we're able to
communicate.
That's how you're able to understand
what I'm saying. So the major first idea
in 2014 or so was actually the idea of
using sequential transduction
and marry it with neural networks. It
was an incredible idea, right? And so
it's [clears throat] very important that
you understand we're not just doing
sequential transduction in the ether. It
was based upon a cognitive understanding
of how our brain worked. That's how
we're able to communicate. That's how
we're able to communicate with our
computers at this point. The amazing
thing is that this model, this new
universal computational model is able to
do convergence.
It's able to take in multimodality data.
It's able to understand all kinds of
different languages all at the same
time. The second big idea from that
10-year period came from a basic
question that Danny Zhao and I were
asking in Google Brain, which was, can
we teach machines the way we teach our
children? It turns out there was a one
dominant way in which we were doing it
wrong. How were we doing it wrong? When
you teach your kids, I hope every time
they get it wrong, you don't just hit
them.
But that was the way that we were
teaching our machines.
Danny and I thought maybe we should give
them an explanation why they are wrong.
That came out with the idea of chain of
thought, right? Give them an
explanation. This is how you do it and
then have them follow the recipe for how
to solve problems. This is known as
top-down processing.
these days in our industry in my
personal opinion we actually have way
too much bottom up processing
particularly using RL when in fact we
should be teaching machines the way that
we teach kids with more top- down
processing
give them explanations so if you think
about it how are we able to distill one
model into another it's all because of
chain of thought the reasoning traces so
the emergence of this idea
of going from next token prediction that
was enabled by sequential transduction
into next idea prediction using train of
thought was the key move that uh started
the whole reasoning field.
Now so in retrospect I wish we had not
called it large language models rather
we should have been calling them large
reasoning models because what we really
care about is their ability to reason.
So there were three ideas therefore in
2015 to 2025 that really matter. The
first one sequential transduction. The
second one next idea prediction with
chain of thought. The third one is post
training. And there are plenty of talks
here on this stage talking to you about
how post training is done and all the
latest advances that's going on there.
Now what are the emerging ideas in the
next 10 years from 2025 to 2035 let's
say? Well, what if all of this ecosystem
starts to change? For example, if you if
didn't didn't realize a single V8 TPU
chip now is 4.7 times more computation
than the C create Cray YMP that I show
you at the beginning of the talk. That's
definitely going to burn a hole in your
pocket.
And what is it enabling? Let's take a
look at a short video. I get a gift from
my friend and this is everything she's
been reading. How would you describe her
taste in books?
>> Based on these titles, your friend seems
to enjoy a mix of history, biography,
and perhaps a touch of political or
social commentary.
>> I picked some of these out. Any idea
which one she'd like the most?
>> Consider Half of a Yellow Sun for its
exploration of complex social and
political issues within a historical
setting, aligning with her interest in
narratives that offer insight into
significant periods.
Now that is not just sorting and ranking
anymore, is it? Okay, that is where
personal assistance is going. Last year
when I was on stage here, I showed this
slide.
Okay, that was more than a year ago. Now
everybody is talking about agents.
The ideas were already there. The next
ideas of the next decade is already
happening. And Richard just talked about
self-improvement for example. There have
been other speakers that talk about
multimodality tool use, multi-step
complex reasoning. My main work at
Google at this point is just focused
around reasoning and planning because
that is where the future is.
Thank you very much.
[applause]
Thank you, Ed. Our third speaker goes by
do he led material science and chemistry
at Google brain and Google deep mind
where he led the work behind Gnome which
discovered over 2 million new crystals.
In last year he co-ounded periodic labs
with Liam Fetis building AI research
agents that are paired with autonomous
labs that run experiments end to end um
with high temperature supercondiv
conductivity as one of the northstars
that they're pursuing. So that would be
amazing as as a physicist. I would love
if that's if they achieve their goal.
Um, if you want to know what happens
when the reward signal comes from a
furnace instead of coming from a unit
test, this is really one to pay
attention to. So, please welcome Dos.
Hello everyone. Um, my name is Do
Chubuk. I'm a co-CEO and co-founder of
Periodic Labs. and we combine
simulations,
experiments and LLMs try to accelerate
physical R&D.
So for the next few minutes, I want to
talk about whether AGI either today's AI
capability or the future AI capability
could just zero shot the next big
scientific breakthrough. And I say it
has to be zero shot because the
breakthrough by definition can't be in
the training set. So it must be
something that's different than what's
been done before. So it has to be done
without previous demonstration for the
breakthrough. You know another way of
thinking about this is can thinkism ever
be enough for advancing physics. So
thinkism is this idea that you lock
yourself in a room and you have all the
textbooks, all the previous experiments,
papers, patents ever been done in the
field and if you think really hard uh
whether you're a human or AGI or AI uh a
bunch of agents can you advance physics
and I will argue for the next few
minutes the answer is no because the
universe is too complex for any
intelligence whether it's humans
or machines to think their way into the
scientific advance. Uh so what's the
alternative? The alternative is what
we've done for centuries, which is you
iterate with the universe. You have a
hypothesis, you try it, it usually
doesn't work on the first one, but you
learn from your failure and then you
keep trying.
So one very interesting history to the
study for this topic is the history of
superconductivity.
um you know if you study history of
superc conductivity you learn a lot
about humans science scientists academic
publishing archive etc but today I'll
just focus on a few things so the
superconductivity for the first time was
discovered back in 1911 and it was not
discovered because a incredible human
just thought really hard and then said
okay if you take mercury and figure out
how to lower the temperature electrons
will feel an attractive force through
phonance. No, what happened is um
Anest's lab, this lab led by Camelang
Anes for the first time created a
capability they can lower the
temperature below any temperature
recorded
before and it was around 4 Kelvin. Um
they got it down to 1.8 eight but turns
out for some metal like mercury if you
can get it to 4 Kelvin it will
superconduct. So it was actually a side
project of the main effort which was to
liquefy helium and a few years later an
got a Nobel prize but very important to
note Nobel prize was not given to
superconductor discovery it was given to
the fact that he could liquefy helium.
Um, and if you look at the rest of the
history, it's full of examples like this
where the big innovation wasn't done
fully intentionally and it wasn't done
by thinking really hard, but it was done
by trying a bunch of things and
iterating intelligently with the
universe. So another really good example
is around 1958, John Bardin and
collaborators figured out the theory of
BCA superconductivity. So this is
conventional superconductivity and it's
great right now the humans understand
how superc conductivity works we can use
that understanding to discover lots of
other superconductors but that's not
really what happened. So if you follow
this curve from 1958 to around 2000,
there's been really major advances into
conventional superconductivity, the
biggest one, the soda in um deep
learning language is magnesium dyoride,
MGB2. But if you look at how that was
discovered, it was not discovered by
humans taking the theory, thinking
really hard and making the material. It
was more like they were trying tens of
thousands of materials and that
particular one happened to be a really
good BCS superconductor. And of course
the other really good example is the
coupe rates around 1986 Alex Mueller and
collaborator were able to find the first
high temperature superconductor the
unconventional one. But if you look at
his Nobel Prize speech you realize he
was actually trying to find a
conventional superconductor because he
didn't even know what an unconventional
superconductor would be. So this is just
for superconductors. But if you look at
other aspects of material science,
chemistry, solid state physics. So I'm
not talking about math and theoretical
computer science. I think that's a
different regime. But if you look at
complex systems like physics, chemistry,
material science, you realize that most
things were found by either accident or
a bunch of trial and error. Okay. So if
this is the case, what does this mean
for agents and LLMs? So I think we're
fine. We just have to figure out how to
use agents in the scientific method that
we've been using for hundreds of years.
So a very simple way of looking at it,
right? We have some observations, we
come up with an hypothesis, we try the
hypothesis through an experiment and
then we look at the result. It will
probably not work very well in the first
time, but we understand why it failed
and we try again. So this is the typical
scientific method. But how we can
improve this with LLMs and agents and
machine learning is we can insert it in
a bunch of places. So one example I can
give is the simulation part in the very
middle. So the simulations are already
completely revolutionized by machine
learning. So today we use uh force
fields which uh approximate quantum
mechanics of the ground state and I
can't even if there's another AI winter
I can't imagine ever not using machine
learning anymore for force fields
another example is of course alpha fold
now we figured out how to do protein
folding way better than before thanks to
machine learning but force fields alpha
fold these are all tools right they
don't actually give us the next big drug
or the next big superconductor but
they're very useful tools And there are
other tools of course such as
characterization which helps us look at
the experimental data and figure out
what happened. It's very technical but
AI can really automate and scale that
up. And at Berkeley here there's been
some frontier work showing how you can
use robotic arms to try a bunch of
things in the lab for synthesizing
powders and characterization is the
obvious um thing you can improve with
AI. Another example is literature search
going through all the papers and
figuring out what other ideas to try and
of course DOE design of experiment where
based on all the experiments you've seen
so far what should be the next
experiment so in our company and outside
our company AI is making a huge impact
on all of these parts and of course it's
not this clean it's actually much more
complicated it's a spaghetti plot where
everything interacts with each other but
you can easily see how the whole
scientific method can accelerate if we
put AI in it intentionally and uh
carefully. So my last slide here I just
want to say in my opinion and in our
company's opinion this universe is too
complex for thinkism alone to innovate.
So instead of looking at the current LLM
progress and getting discouraged
especially if you're a science student
you should think the opposite. It's
actually really exciting time to do
science and what I would recommend is to
fully focus on understanding the
fundamentals. If you're a physicist, you
know, study the theory of superc
conductivity, study solid state
chemistry. If you're a biologist, study
what's important in biology, I don't
know. And really understand the
scientific fundamentals,
experimentation, because you realize
that a lot of progress happened when
people came up with new experimental
methods, new techniques, new measurement
tools. And you can contribute to all of
these. And as you create new
experimentation methods, new tools, then
AI will benefit from it because AI will
see more data and it'll be able to use
this thinkism skill to make sense out of
it faster in bigger scale. And then
hopefully the next experiment you try is
more successful and more intelligent.
Thank you. [applause]
Thank you, D. So now I have the pleasure
of introducing myself, but I'll keep it
really, really quick so we can get to
the good part. So my name is Ego
Babushkin. Um, I've been doing Frontier
Research for almost the last 10 years.
So I started out doing AI at Deepmind
where I worked on WaveNet and uh
training Starcraft agents actually then
joined OpenAI uh later to work on
scaling up transformer models and then I
co-ounded XAI together with Elon and
within less than two years we managed to
get to the frontier in in AI. Um, and
now I've started a new company called
RiverAI with the goal to allow each
individual um, more control and
ownership over their AI experience. Um,
and we're really really fascinated by
this new idea of personal AI which also
poses a lot of tough and really really
interesting uh, research challenges and
that's what I want to talk about um,
today.
So, oh doesn't seem to be working.
Oh, we might have a problem with the
slides actually.
I mean, I I can improvise everything
without the slides, but would be good to
have good to have them.
Let's let's give them a few seconds to
um to resolve it, and I'll just I'll
just keep talking. So, um like I
mentioned previously, this year we've
seen this enormous breakthrough with
coding agents. So, they've really
achieved um know massive economic
appeal. uh you can build a whole super
profitable uh tech company around this
idea of serving coding agents. Um but
everybody sort of feels in their bones
that um this is not the end, right? So
something what's the next big thing that
will come and one advantage that um
um yeah
like oh we've got we actually have
slides here coming up. Very very nice.
So one advantage that you have in the
coding domain is that you have
verifiable rewards. So the agent writes
code it um um and then we have a unit
test or some other verifiable way to
ensure that what the agent did was
correct and then we can give a reward
signal and then you can leverage all the
tools from reinforcement learning uh to
to basically improve that agent make it
extremely powerful and that's what led
what has led to the success today and um
I think everybody agreed that coding is
one of these fundamental building blocks
that you want to solve before moving on
to other domains. So that's that's an
easy one, but what comes after that? So
and actually I see multiple directions
now, some of which you've heard today.
So I think this idea of scientific
discovery of the agent becoming more and
more intelligent, maybe improving
itself, discovering even better
algorithms and increasing its own
intelligence is one. Automating the
economy is also something that a lot of
people are talking about. How can we
bring agents into all aspects of the
economy? Every company out there
automating the work. Um and then there's
this other direction that I'm personally
very passionate about that's personal
AI. So this is for me this is the idea
that um each one of us will have a
digital entity this personal agent that
accompanies us uh that understands us
really really deeply that can
proactively reach out to us and uh
essentially can improve our lives can
make them can make it happier can make
it go more smoothly and perhaps this can
actually be uh the next big computing
paradigm because now we've seen um lots
of developments the personal computer,
the mobile phone, the internet, uh, and
perhaps digital entities that understand
us deeply and that assist us could be
the next big development. We've actually
seen some know early examples of these
personal air systems like OpenClaw or
Hermes agent, but if you've played with
these, I think you'll understand that
there's not not that huge mass market
appeal yet. So, you have to tinker quite
a bit with it. You have to maintain it
really well. And there are some big big
problems that haven't been solved yet.
Um once we do figure out how to solve
them, I think this is could be a really
interesting future to live in where you
know we don't just have human or human
relationships but we also have
relationships with these digital
entities that are optimized uh to help
us to understand us deeply to get things
done for us. So um this is the kind of
future that I think I want to I want to
live in. Um but to get there um there
are at least five problems that haven't
been solved yet that are really really
um serious. So one problem is you
actually want to optimize for the
personal AI use case. So you want to run
reinforcement learning for personal AI.
Today's personal AI systems, they're
often coding agents that are
generalizing the personal AI use case.
So we really want to figure out how to
do our training for personal AI.
Personalization has to be something that
we solve because if you have an agent
that's running 247 in the background
that's doing things autonomously then it
better have a really good understanding
of how to help you. So that's important.
Memory and long context are crucial
because some of these tasks they could
span a whole 24 hours or multiple days.
Privacy and security are super super
difficult problems because today maybe
have things like prompt injection.
Imagine that your friend or not or or
your enemy texts your personal AI agent
a string that then allows them to take
it over and they can get all your
secrets. So we have to prevent that. And
then lastly, a big one is cost. So if
you add up how many tokens do you
consume if the agent runs 24/7 in the
background and how much does it cost?
You can easily get to thousands of
dollars a month. It really becomes
prohibitive for most people. Um so these
are the big challenges that we want to
solve. there's also an opportunity to
change the game when it comes to
ownership and control of AI. So, so
currently with the current paradigm,
coding agents and so on, a lot of
control sits with the AI companies that
provide um LLM APIs and if we kind of go
through you know the uh development of
of computing with mainframes then
personal computers became a thing, the
smartphone um happened and so on. Now
cloud AI is sort of a step away from
giving the indigo control. This you
don't have the physical device. You
don't have the means for doing
inference. Um but personal AI
potentially could be a way of uh getting
back into that regime where you maybe
have a physical device in your home or
in your office that um contains the
model weights that stores your private
data which is more secure which is
better for privacy. So um it's not
something that's guaranteed but it's an
opportunity for us to build something
you know that's really for the benefit
of the individual. So let me now quickly
jump into a few of these research
directions. I only have very very little
time so I can go into depth um here but
how would you tackle something like
agent memory for example. So I believe
there are really sort of two different
philosophies about how to handle agent
memory. One is the idea that memory
should be handled in context. So as a
memory system that the agent can access
and a lot of the information is
transformed transferred via tokens or
text. So you might be able to to
retrieve a phone number or you might be
able to retrieve a past conversation
that you've had. And the other
philosophy is to actually update the
model at the weight level. And I believe
each of these have different advantages
and disadvantages for at the weight
level. It's really hard to store
individual facts like a phone number or
somebody's name. Um and in in the end
context world, it's really hard uh to
store those implicit that implicit
knowledge like what's the preference
what are the preferences of my user? um
what's the style in which they're
writing their emails, you know, maybe
can I imitate that? Um but it's so hard
to to specify in in a text file. Um so I
believe we need both of these and here
are some research papers that go into
details that provide approaches for how
you could implement memory systems with
both philosophies. Um there's also the
direction of personalization. So how do
we actually align this model not just
with the the whole population of users
but with the individual user that it's
serving? And like I mentioned, I think
this is really important for the agent
to reliably represent you and
successfully do things for you in the
background. Um, and there are sort of
two two philosophies here about how to
personalize.
One is more on the passive side. So
observe what the user is doing. Um,
basically leverage all of the data that
they're generating in their life. The
other one is more of an active approach
or probe the user to to understand their
preferences. Um, or directly optimize
against their feedback. So if I'm
telling the agent this was good, this
was not so good, then we want to update
the model weights or update the prompt
of the system to for it to become better
and better for you. And there's also a
lot of activity in terms of research
happening here across these these
different domains. Um so a few research
paper papers I've also mentioned I'm
also showing here. Um so feel free to to
take a look at these. And um another
category here is infrastructure because
personal AI might actually require a
whole different set of tools and um
newly deployed infrastructure than what
we have today. And so two kind of
directions that have emerged around
personal AI that I think are really
really interesting and can actually be
be useful today are um one on the one
side the approach of multi-tenant Laura.
So previously when you wanted to train
your model you have to update all the
weights of the model and they're in the
trillions of parameters these days. So
people found out that you can add these
so-called Laura adapters which only
represent a small fraction of the
weights and only modify those during
training and this opens up a lot of
possibilities for how to do post
training and RL more efficiently and can
even open up the possibility of having
one custom fine-tuned model per user in
the future. can also experiment with
continue learning um using these tools.
So these are really really powerful
toolboxes and at RiverAI we've also
built our own multi-tenant Laura um
system which we've released. Um and on
the other end we have a local hardware.
So that's there's an opportunity there
to basically move your inference from
the data center to a local device um
that's in either in your hand or maybe
in your home or in your office. And um
today that's uh people are starting to
explore this but there are still a lot
of opportunities. There's a lot of
lowhanging fruit in terms of how to
optimize these local inference systems.
And it's it's possible that a local
inference might actually start to rival
the data center um inference one day.
The big bottleneck there is model
capacity. How do you fit these trillions
and trillions of parameters into a small
form factor and how do you do inference
efficiently without know overheating
your your home? Um, today it requires a
whole rack of GPUs to be able to do
this, but in the future, um, you know,
we're hoping this might be just a single
device. So, if you're interested in this
kind of new infrastructure, I couldn't
resist, you know, plugging our own
product here, please check out
river.ai/appi AI/ API um for our
multi-tenant Laura system that allows
you to do research on post training and
RL very effectively and also um allows
you to explore continue learning and
some of these new ideas that are that
are now coming out of academia. So um
yeah by the way this whole thing was
written by my personal agent u because I
was pretty lazy today but um yeah thank
you so much. So, we now have a a little
panel discussion. We have 20 to to 30
minutes. So, I'll invite the the
speakers to come back out and we'll sit
down and we'll talk a little bit about
what it's like to do research at the
frontier. And I have a few questions
I've prepared. So,
all right folks. Um, so like I
mentioned, coding agents have been
tremendously successful. Now we're all
wondering uh what's the next big thing?
What is the next step? And you've
presented you know your personal
directions for this. So um one one
feature that I think is pretty common
among all of the new directions that
people are pursuing is it's getting
harder and harder to generate those
rewards that are we can use to power
reinforcement learning. Right? So I'm
curious um how do you think about um the
the difficulty of getting rewards in
your particular domain? Do you think
there are ways of um new new techniques
you can use to get those rewards or how
do how do you think of this? So starting
with Ed maybe.
>> Yeah. Um the the difficulty with rewards
is really because the predominant
paradigm over the last couple years have
been about um using correctness as a
feedback to the RL process. And the
reward functions were pretty easy to um
to build when you have a correctness um
that's built into the question that
you're asking. But there are many
questions that we want to ask including
in science as Richard was mentioning
that um the answer may not be correct or
not correct maybe more somewhere in
between you know um and the challenge in
building those reward functions
um it's not just in in in figuring out
you know sort of some approximate
solution to that but is rather that the
RL process is very very good at finding
loopholes um in the reward function when
it's not a black and white kind of uh
answer. So that we call this reward
hacking um in the actual development of
the algorithms and we see it manifest in
actually model instabilities
um when we have these more complicated
reward functions. Um so uh to to
summarize therefore I think one way to
think about this whole RL thing and
using correctness function is as I
mentioned in my talk it's a little bit
like teaching your kids when it's wrong
you just slap them in their butt and
then you know you don't give them any
more explanation why they were wrong
right other than just figure it out. Um
and so I think this kind of bottom up
training process is actually a very
sorry for saying it this way but uh it's
a very dumb way of teaching
>> right
>> um I think actually what we're seeing
with distillation and SFT coming back
into vogue what we're seeing is actually
a lot more top- down processing in
teaching you know where um some people
find it distasteful because it feels
like we're using human brains to teach
machine brains if you will and it
doesn't feel as emergent but um but that
that's what I believe is that uh we need
to have more top- down processing uh
injected into the to the AI training
process.
>> Thank you. Yeah, Josh, how are things
looking with the furnace? Is it
generating rewards?
>> Yeah. So, um there are two kinds of
issues with furnaces, right? So, one of
them is um as Ed mentioned, you don't
always know if the thing worked or not.
like you take the thing out of the
furnace, it's not actually obvious. It
might have partially worked. Um, and in
fields where LLMs and RL has made a huge
impact, I think there are two specific
things that really help. One is there is
a very clear yes or no. Uh, we just
talked about this. The other one is the
how much of the variables are in the
context. So, you know, when you're
programming, when you're doing
theoretical computer science, math, all
the context you might need could be
available to the LM. The problem with
physics is right, we have more atoms
than we can track. And this is why
thermodynamics was a big deal because in
the 19th century we realized instead of
having to model 10^ the 23 atoms that
you know make up a mole of um matter,
you can just use a few variables like
pressure, energy, volume etc. Uh so we
have to give up on providing all the
relevant context to the LLM because
there's no way we can do that. So then
the question is what can we provide and
is it sufficient? That's why it's really
important to add as much metrology
characterization as possible, maybe even
more than before, and just provide as
much context as possible about what
happened in the furnace or in the thin
film chamber to the LLM.
>> I I think those are all really
interesting. I mentioned it in the UK
machine, right? You have human current
knowledge. Uh you have scientific
measurements. Then you have simulations
which are you know hard at scale uh in
with current computers and then you have
to have real life experiments and then
hopefully you can get some of those uh
inner loops uh resolved. I think in
terms of reward functions there's also
this whole idea um that I've been
thinking about recently on meta
cognition. Uh I think if you truly have
something that's super intelligent it
wouldn't just robotically do exactly
what you ask it to. Right? there's uh in
some sense no research right now on
subjective functions rather than
objective functions that we're all
working on right uh and so uh one way
that you can these can emerge is if you
give AI the right environment uh that is
not as easily reward hackable which I
think is the number one concern for
safety also it's just alignment but I do
have to say that I'm sort of cautiously
optimistic and I want to maybe invite
folks to see whisper flow which is like
a voice recognition app uh of sorts as a
first sign of things to come as AI gets
better. Whisper flow doesn't exactly
write what you say. It writes what you
mean. Uh and most AI currently does very
poorly like exactly do what you say like
make this benchmark number go higher
>> but you didn't mean like by hacking
hugging face you know like and so but I
think eventually uh that that will get
resolved.
>> Cool. So, one thing I'm really curious
about because these agents, they have
this promise of accelerating us. Are you
actually seeing real world acceleration
from using your models? Uh, so Richard,
how are things looking at at recursive?
>> It is kind of nuts. Like I [laughter]
like I really think like we have a
fairly small team, but they act as if
they're like an order of magnitude more
people.
>> Um, it's much [clears throat] less about
headcount these days than it is about
agent count. And if you want to, you
know, yield uh like and and wield sort
of like hundreds or or even several
thousands of agents, you need a lot of
compute. And so I think the future in
which a lot of these forward-leaning
organizations actually use more compute
uh or spend more on compute than on uh
on headcount uh and people is not like
is very likely uh to happen especially
at the frontier. Um and [clears throat]
yeah, I would love to hear from you
actually also on like how much robotic
process automation can you do now and is
the bottleneck the intelligence or
actually just the mechanics. M
>> I mean for the experimental side I feel
like the biggest bottleneck is
characterization and analysis
>> because you know it's not too hard to
just mix things and then try a thousand
things at the same time but what's
really hard is to understand what you
actually made and um this is actually
really good news because AI can do
really well at this like you can show AI
how to do for example XRD refinement how
to use read well refinement tools um use
simulations in the loop group u and it's
like doing characterization analysis
well isn't as hard as discovering
something new it's just like using the
tools correctly and I think this is
great news for science because now we
can try many more things and intelligent
analyze them before um of course we do a
lot of coding like the the theoretical
physicists do coding the
experimentalists do coding and LLMs have
completely revolutionized it of course
uh also on the simulation side so force
fields are these uh things that people
have used for more than a century to
approximate quantum mechanics. I think
one could argue that even Einstein's
first paper was a force field paper and
in the last 10 years because of graph
neural networks force fields changed
permanently and it's amazing now how
much of the periodic table we can model
without even doing quantum chemistry. Um
so yeah really exciting on the
capabilities side
>> are people at Google using agents to
accelerate themselves? Yeah, we're
obviously using agents uh in our um
coding work. Um but I think as uh
Richard and Do were just describing, I
was realizing that um maybe I think
about the problem a little bit from a
weird way, if you will. Um, you know,
the reality is that I think about that
is is that it has been a decent amount
of tension that's happened ever since
the beginning of of uh sort of sort of
the uh chain of thought era is that um
agent harnesses is really the evolution
of prompt engineering to today, right?
Like because people started with prompts
and then they figured out that they can
put more things in the prompt to get the
model to do what it they wanted it to
do. Then they realized they should
programmably put these prompt together.
Then they figured out things like lang
chain to figure out how to chain prompts
together. So to get it to do more
complex tasks. Then they realized they
can just put a whole program around the
generation of the prompt and how many
prompts and how to chain them together.
And then that evolved into agent
harnesses and coding harnesses. So that
whole evolution of course all of us have
been in the field and been watching that
going. But the tension that is inherent
in your question is um there have been
for three four years um this debate
about how much should be in the model
and how much should it be in the
programmable framework the agent harness
that we call it now. we just we used to
just call it programmable LOM
frameworks. Um and in in fact I'm sure
in the audience today there are people
who are trying out different agent
harnesses with different models and
they're realizing that you know they're
kind of evaluating all pairs of these
relationship like they're using a strong
very structured agent harness working
with a very weak model and then they
when they have a very strong model they
try to put less harness around it. By
the way, it's just very interesting to
me that we use the word harness.
>> You know, the the word harness obviously
comes from horses.
[laughter] The reason why we're called
engines horsepower is because the
industrial revolution, you know, with
engines, we all became engineers, right?
Like we're supposed to work on engines,
right? Like tightening screws and stuff
like that. And then, you know, the
engine mount is basically the harness,
right? So the reality is the the the
prompt engineering and the harness is
kind of like the structure that's trying
to get the engine to do what we want it
to do,
>> right? So this this tension between the
harness and the model capability and
people are realizing when you have a
strong model, you should use a weaker
prompting technique and weaker
programmable harnesses. But when you
have a weaker model, you could mitigate
its capabilities using a stronger
harness, you know, a more structure. Um
but however I think people are also
coming to the realization when they do
this that the two together can only
reach a particular performance level and
there is a plateau that we see we can't
seem to go over at the current moment
and that is actually the major um
bottleneck or or barrier currently
facing the industry in my opinion.
>> Yeah that's the frontier the
>> that's literally the frontier right now
actually. Yeah, maybe jamming on that. I
do think the whole field of AI is kind
of stuck below what I call enthropic
bounds. Not just the the company, but
like this idea that like we measure
models in terms of ELO scores of what
you which human said this model is
better than that model. We we measure a
lot of our benchmarks based on how many
of the human-designed labels and human
designed classes and task did you get
right in this subset of you know images
and uh like reasoning questions and so
on. All of those have implicit and
sometimes very explicit human bounds.
Like if you're, you know, 100, you can
get 100 out of 100% of the like uh
questions right,
>> then that's the maximum you can get to.
And yeah, maybe humans get like 95 and
you get like 5% above the human
baseline, but that's it. Where do you go
from there? And the only way to get out
of that is through simulations and some
verifiers where you can then get
superhuman capabilities or in these
open-ended evolutionary uh environments.
>> Well, now I have a really really tough
question. So let's see if one of you can
can find an answer here. But
>> get ready for this one.
>> So um we're all at the frontier and at
the frontier you need access to
tremendous compute resources. You've got
colleagues that are experts in their in
their field. But there are so many
people in academia and know especially
PhD students out there who don't get
access to those resources today but they
still want to contribute to the
frontier. They want to uh to contribute
to agents and the future of agents. Um
do you have any tips for those folks?
like what are the directions what are
the ideas that they should focus on uh
where there's a potential to have big
impact with fewer resources and
contribute to to these frontier efforts
like anyone uh that
>> that's something that comes to mind
>> I think there's a ton of opportunity
still um there's so many underexplored
areas and application areas of AI too
sure like maybe the research area of
pre-training and mid and post and RL
training like is not the best one for
PhD students at a university You know, I
had this paper in 2018 on a two-level
reinforcement learning um uh set up uh
called the AI economist where you
essentially had uh agents that just
optimized their own uh utility functions
and you can make assumptions based on
how many hours would people want to work
and some people want to are willing to
work 100hour work weeks and some people
only want to work 10hour work weeks,
right? And then they're kind of
unmotivated. And so, long story short,
you can then have this simulation of
agents that are economic agents trying
to optimize their own utility, collect
resources, block others, build
monopolies, whatever. And then you had
an AI economist that would set taxes and
subsidies uh and basically could now
simulate billions and billions of years
of taxation and subsidization.
Essentially political philosophy and try
to find the sort of best uh way to set
these uh taxation schemes and tax
brackets and so on based on a goal that
you gave it like productivity multiplied
with equality or sustainability or
whatever you politically care about.
middle class like whatever politicians
say right now what's interesting is that
paper never had its sort of GPT moment
where someone actually took that idea
and massively scaled it up and so the
whole field of economics is still like
preai era like when you look at
economists there's one really famous
economist from Berkeley actually say
right he invented this famous sc formula
and it's provably correct in a one-step
economy where there's no adaptation
there's no adjustment or no temporal
sequences and so on. That's the state of
the field of economics. And if you now
realize that AI could do so much more
there and you can simulate people better
and better especially in their aggregate
statistics, you realize like there's so
much low hanging fruit for PhD students
to take AI and apply it to economics.
And that is just one of many examples.
there are still so many other fields uh
that that you can research in and then
combine AI with that are extremely
underexplored and I'm excited that like
venture capital is now excited also
about chemistry and some more physics
and obviously biology uh but there also
is still so much lowhanging fruit um to
apply I to these various scientific
fields
>> any more ideas for the
>> yeah I mean I would say um I mean so
it's hard to predict the future right
like in four years. If these robots are
as dextrous and intelligent, creative,
uh has a sense of style, uh as humans, I
think this answer gets very complicated.
But today, uh I think it's very easy to
say robots are not as dextrous. They're
not as creative. Uh they don't really
have a sense of interestingness. And in
that case, I think what the students
should study in my opinion is the
fundamentals. So you know uh for example
today very practically if somebody as a
scientist applies to periodic labs to me
it doesn't make too much of a difference
if they've been using agentic tools to
run simulations because you know there's
something you can probably learn how to
do pretty quickly. The thing that's very
unique and unfortunately getting more
and more rare is just people who
understand the fundamentals about like
the physics you're studying or the
experiments you're studying. I mean I I
used to joke but um when I was at Google
we used to have these you know interns
coming in and I used to hire interns
from physics labs to do physics research
and they'd be so much stronger on the
machine learning than the physics and
you know and you know maybe I'm just
being like too uh uncreative here
because back then I used to worry that
as you know all the simulation tools are
in forran and C and C++ and all the kids
are only doing Python. I was like, "Oh,
are we screwed?" Like, "What's going to
happen in the future?" But I think
that's resolved now, right? Like now,
even though we don't have it yet, we can
see that these agents will be able to
give us Python code or Jack's code given
a forrand package. Great. Um, but there
are still a lot of things that these
machines cannot do like um being
creative about the fundamentals, coming
up with like a true innovation on our
understanding of the universe, being
able to run experiments, coming up with
new experiments. So at least like from
my selfish perspective I really feel
like the big alpha today is understand
the fundamentals of the application and
then you can connect it with machine
learning.
Um
in when I was working at Google brain
when do and I were both in Google brain
um when we were before the uh chain of
thought era um I remember Danny Zhao and
came to me and he said you know all
those people in Google brain with
control on over the resources makes it
very difficult for me to do research you
know so the same complaint in a way that
you're kind
inherent in the in the question that
you're asking and he said to me um how
do I deal with this problem? I said I
don't know you know go think about how
human think and maybe we can figure out
a way to like inject these processes
into the model and and then one day he
came to me and and and what I'm about to
tell you I hope doesn't get me fired
from Google by the way um one day he
came to me and he said um I I want to do
a bunch of experiment on GPT is that
allowed and it's like because we're at
Google we should should be using palm
that was the our model right so we
should be using palm And it's like I
can't get my hands on chips to do all
these experiment on palm. I don't have
access to the checkpoints blah blah blah
blah blah. And I said can can can I just
use GPT? Who who will pay for it? And I
pulled out my credit card and I said
here's my credit card. So he charged all
these like API usage on this is before
chat GPT. Okay. So this is no free
resources. You actually have to buy API
API key and all that. He racked up
couple couple thousand dollars worth of
charges or something like that. and then
we wrote the paper. Uh that was uh that
became uh chain of thought. So even then
you know Google was spending billions of
dollars already to train these large
language models. And here comes a new
idea that was top down rather than
bottom up. Um not train not thinking
about next token prediction but rather
thinking about next idea prediction. And
I think we ultimately spent less than
$10,000 to come up with the next idea.
Now you might say, "Oh, wow. That was
three, four years ago." I think the
paper was January of Januaryish of 2022
21. Um, and and so you say, "Oh, well
then that's not possible in 2026." Well,
where were you when Peter Steinberger
was working on Open Claw, right? Like I
would argue a lot of people really
started to pay attention to agent
gentech programming framework when he
really put all these technology together
and that didn't cost like billions of
dollars, right? He was just some dude I
think he presented yesterday. I was
flying in from Taiwan last night and so
I didn't get to attend his talk but I
mean here's a guy who just like oh I'm
going to experiment with Gentech
frameworks and then he come up with some
new thing uh about how to think about
the problem. So I think the state that
we're in um you know that when academia
are complaining about this it's a little
bit like there are many mature fields
that have moved like this like
experimental physics at some point
people are going to complain I don't
have access to a linear accelerator or
when I was working on supercomputing
back in the 90s oh I didn't have access
to a create YMP you know so therefore I
don't have 2.6 six gigaflops or whatever
it is to do. By the way, does anyone
know why we were investing in
supercomputer in 1990? Does anyone know?
Anyone can raise their Yeah. What what's
the reason?
>> What kind of simulations?
>> Nuclear.
>> That's right. Nuclear simulations. It
was because of a nuclear ban treaty. We
wanted to simulate real physical
processes. So, we built supercomputers.
That was the reason. And then people
started, you know, that was came from a
complaint about the fact that we can't
blow things up anymore. So we're gonna
have to like come up with a new way uh
understanding physics, right? And that
was supercomputers. So we're very good
at coming up with new ways of looking at
old problems as well as new problems. Um
and so I think computer science as a
field or AI as a field needs to continue
to look at this. When everybody is
working on RL, you should be thinking
what's the next idea. Yeah, it's kind of
interesting like you touch on an
interesting point which is like I still
remember in 2010 when I submitted my
first neural nets for NLP papers, they
got desk rejected. People are like we
don't do neural nets in NLP conferences.
They didn't even look at the
experiments. And even when we uh
submitted a paper for prompt engineering
where you had one neural network to
answer any and all kinds of questions,
the reviewers literally said that it
makes no sense. you should never have
one model to try to answer different
kinds of questions. They should all be
different models and like it was like
unfathomable for them and they rejected
that paper too. It's all public on open
review and that ICLR submission on DECA
NLP. The paper eventually got cited five
times by the first GBT paper and like
you know it kind of had its run now but
like there's now almost like a
monoculture that is like similar to the
monoculture from 2010 when it's all
anti- neural nets and now it's like
almost all only neural nets. So I think
it'll be good to start thinking again
about completely different approaches.
um uh you know not everything is a
transformer. Transformer is just one
like one sample in a very large
equivalence class and I think there are
other better classes of algorithms still
to be explored. Uh I think compute
substrates obviously we can do better
like we know the brain has more flops
per watt than any of the hardware we
have. So there's like so much research
there still to be done and so on. I'm
like I feel like there's no excuse for
researchers in AI and outside of AI not
to still do like academic work.
>> Yeah, there's a good lesson in
resilience there for PhD students as
well. Just because your paper gets
rejected, you know, it could still be
the next big breakthrough. Nobody really
knows the future. So, um yeah, it's a
lot of folks in the field tell me
similar stories about their big big
breakthroughs. Um, one thing I would add
is, um, while the research at the
frontier is getting more and more
expensive and challenging, at the same
time, we're also seeing some of the
tools being more and more democratized.
So, I'm thinking especially of open
weight models for example. So, if you
wanted to start off with a really
capable LLM or really capable agent, you
can actually take a powerful open weight
model today and then do a lot of
interesting research and development on
on top of that. And even the tools for
post- training and reinforcement
learning are getting democratized. I
mentioned the river AI API earlier and
Tinker is another example of these kinds
of tools where even with a very limited
budget you can do really really
interesting work. So I think it's also a
big opportunity for for researchers um
to be able to do really actually
frontier work um without u a huge cost
um attached to it. So we're getting to
the end of the session. So I wanted to
go to the big big closing statement and
so wanted to ask you folks um let's make
a prediction for the next 12 months.
We've seen this year was the year of
coding agents and the incredible
economic success um that they that came
with them. Um over the next 12 months
what will be the next big agent
breakthrough? What do where do you see
the big um impact in the world and
economic impact as well? So maybe
starting with with that.
>> Um well as uh many of you know if you
especially attended last year's um uh
summit um I was making a prediction that
personalization was going to be really
big and I know Richard has also worked
on personalization as well. It's been
very surprising how slow it has been to
be perfectly honest.
>> Um but I think a lot of the issue has
been around data um and the sparity of
data for personalization. I um on in the
consumer space uh my prediction in the
next 12 months or so would be that uh
we'll we'll be usually it takes like a
three tries for these things to succeed
and I think there will be a good try
probably within the next 12 month or so
uh in this space and and most of the
issues will be centered around two
things. One is data that I mentioned the
integration. Um the other is actually
having to do with being able to really
make good inductive uh inferences and
reasoning. Um because so much of the
model these days are very focused around
deductive reasoning. You bought this
therefore I think you were going to buy
this next. Like you bought a bicycle, so
you're going to need tires or something
like that, right? Like there's a
reasoning chain that's very deductive
like that. Um but actually a lot of the
recommendation tasks, the
personalization tasks are very ambiguous
and need they need more induction,
right? Like um you know you're if you
bought a turntable, we can infer that
maybe you like classical music for
example or jazz. I'm a big vinyl
collector. So by the way, one of the
reason I came up to Berkeley is because
Rasp Putin is not far away from here. So
I could could walk over and peruse the
aisles there. Um but you know that
that's an example of an induction right
like Google maps should be recommending
hey by the way it's restin is you know
less than five minute walk from here you
should go check it out right so that's
the kind of inductive reasoning I think
in the future in the personalization
space we're going to see within the the
next 12 months
>> you Josh
>> yeah so speaking of induction I think if
you look at what happened so far in
terms of how uh LLMs and agents did
something incredibly different in the
sciences and math. I think it's easy to
say that it's been in math, theoretical
computer science and programming. So if
you were to do induction, the next step
should be fields where um pure theory
goes a long way. So maybe this will be
your expertise with the particle theory
um or maybe it'll be in astrophysics.
I'm not sure. Uh it could also be
computational physics where you know
there's some really difficult problems
in computational physics that's not
necessarily like the real universe but
still very important on its own right.
So it could be that as well. I don't
know if it's going to be in 12 months.
Again, like it's really hard to predict
the future, but it does it does suggest
that like given the current trend that
could be the next step.
>> It feels like math there's a lot of a
lot of results in mathematics coming out
every day now. So getting more and more
theorems proven. So I think that's a
know very promising very promising bet.
Richard,
>> man, it's going to be an exciting 12
months. Um maybe I'll cheat by doing
three. Uh I think number one we'll see
more proactive uh consumer interfaces to
these models uh that capture more and
more of your context and hence we'll
make sort of predict like
recommendations before you ask for them.
Um there are already a few startups that
are growing uh a little bit here and
there uh but I think more of that uh is
to come. Uh I think in biology we're
going to see the first uh and much
faster clinical trials and getting more
and more uh drugs and proteins developed
with AI that are then like succeeding at
a higher rate than currently uh as they
get into later stage trials. And then
we're going to have uh the first baby
forms of recursive self-improvement. Um,
and you know, I'm cheating there cuz the
best predictions are those that you're
going to work on yourself and try to
make them true. So, uh, I think uh, it's
it's feasible. It's it's happening. Um,
we're very confident. And like it's then
of course a question of well, but how
much compute do you give it and how hard
are the tasks that you give it uh to to
work on and the environments and and all
of that. So sometimes people think that
there's going to be this hard takeoff
scenario and despite being extremely
exciting excited and optimistic about
AI, the hard takeoff scenario where
everyone loses their jobs or the AI
kills everyone, all of these are highly
unrealistic sci-fi. And and so I also
predict in the negative that none of the
doomsday scenarios will will happen at
all whatsoever. And just like GPT was
too dangerous to release to the world,
there will be no open source model that
will be too dangerous to release to the
world.
>> Thank you so much. And I hope you all
enjoyed this little glimpse at the at
the frontier.
[applause]
So, let's thank the speakers. Thank you.
>> Nice one.
Okay.
They can't hear me.
>> No,
>> I guess now people can hear me.
[laughter]
>> Uh, I am Megan I edit the Axios
AI Plus newsletter. I have been a tech
journalist for about 25 years. So um
been around and our panel is about
agentic AI developer platforms and I've
been meeting for the last couple of
weeks with all our panelists and you
know trying to figure out what you as an
audience want to hear versus what me as
a journalist want to hear. So hopefully
we have convened on me asking the
questions that these very smart people
uh are going to answer for you today.
And I am going to have them introduce
themselves and let you know what what
layer of the stack uh either most
interests you or most concerns you. Go
ahead.
>> Oh, hi everyone. Um my name is Eva and
I'm one of the co-founders of a company
called Daytona. Daytona is an
infrastructure company that for the most
part offers a CPU cloud um for agent
execution. So, think of everything from
background agents to helping out with um
RL runs.
>> And I'm Matt White. I most recently uh
for the last few years was leading the
our AI initiatives at Linux Foundation.
Uh led the PyTorch Foundation for for a
little over two and a half years. And uh
I think the areas that I'm really
interested in are the sort of
non-competitive spaces where we can
build unified infrastructure for Agentic
AI where we're all coming together
working on common specs and standards to
facilitate a a strong stack that we can
all build on top of.
>> Yeah. Hi everyone. I am Dimma,
co-founder of Fireworks AA. So Fireworks
is also an infrastructure platform
layer. So we help people to build
specialized intelligence basically help
developers and businesses to build this
open models and run inference for that
and uh do a lot of RL and fine tuning on
top of that. In previous life I was u
working on pettor for five years. I was
one of the core maintainers and had the
pleasure to work with Metton Pet
Foundation uh before Fireworks. Um and
yeah, I mean I guess the layer which I'm
most excited about is kind of model
customization and how to enable everyone
to specialize their AI for their
businesses or their needs or their
product.
>> Um I'm Mazen Gilbert. I I run the Aentic
AI Foundation at Linux. So we are a
nonprofit foundation that started six
months ago with uh MCP. Most of you
probably are using MCP and the goal of
the foundation is to drive open-source
and open standard adoption in the
agentic AI space. My interest is um it's
really hard. It's the whole stack is
absolutely fascinating from the hardware
to the applications. But I'm a big
proponent for openness and how openness
drive innovation.
So I want to stop with start with
openness. Uh there's been two big
stories that have been driving the news
cycles. Uh one being uh the open weight
versus closed. uh there's been you know
people lining up on either side mostly
one side and the other side being
anthropic but it's a complicated it's
it's complicated the other story of
course which we're going to get to is is
the frontier models uh breaking out of
testing and compromising third party
websites. Uh so I would like I'd love to
start with the open debate which
admittedly we don't really have anyone
on the closed side here. [laughter]
So uh I I might uh play devil's advocate
but I think open the open weight uh
argument often comes down to safety um
versus safety versus openness. We can't
we can't be safe if we're open. Um so
let's start um
with you Matt. [laughter]
Um what do you think what do you think
when someone says well you know openw
weight models are inherently dangerous.
Um it's an argument we've heard before
uh when uh Lionus Tvales developed Linux
and it was okay open source is you know
the work of the devil and all of this
sort of narrative from from uh Steve
Balmer at the time. Uh the and we've
heard it's through cryptography too
right like cryptography was okay it's
going to allow criminals to to to do bad
things. Um most technologies are dual
use right and AI is no different. Um, I
think the argument can be made that if
you're building at the frontier and that
model has some capabilities that may
impact society negatively, then I think
the labs need to think about whether
they should be releasing that or not.
But it ultimately the argument that you
know frontier level especially when we
talk about like cyber
um is that everybody should be able to
defend their infrastructure. Everybody
should have that ability to patch their
infrastructure and if that's centrally
administrated it won't take long before
an open model from somewhere else comes
along that has those capabilities and
then the attackers are suddenly at a
huge advantage. And so I think openness
levels the playing field uh when it
comes to you know when it comes to
safety
>> we were talking behind uh back in the
green room about uh how your foundation
really covers both sides and uh so talk
a little bit about uh how you see the
future in the open versus closed. Yeah,
I so number one we have members in the
foundation who are building both open
and closed uh from the anthropic open AI
of the world to the others. Um so number
one whether it's open or closed there is
an accountability
um on every company who's building a
model on ensuring they've run the
benchmarks the tests uh and ensuring
those models are safe basically to use
and and they have to be transparent on
these tests what tests were run and how
safe these models for others basically
to use and and that transparency is not
completely there today and that's an
area that we need to drive more as an
ecosystem system and standardize. So it
becomes a practice for every model
provider. But generally just like with
every open and this is no different
whether it's a o whether we're talking
about models or code when something is
open it means everybody has access to
it. Everybody have access to try it to
test it um to change it uh to improve
it. And uh very different than closed
where only a handful of people behind
closed doors who are actually only have
access to that and what you have access
to is just an API. So generally we've
seen open to be safer uh because it's
open to everybody. There are enough
contributors to looking at that. This is
how Unix is. Unix is open. This is how
Kubernetes is. Kubernetes is open.
PyTorch which math was part of that.
PieTorch is open. So if you look at a
lot of the major revolutions that's
happened in the history, it's all been
because it was open.
>> Is it as simple as you know OpenAI and
Anthropic, they're going to IPO? They
they need money. So let's keep our
secrets. Is it that simple?
>> Well, I don't know. Like from the other
hand, if you look at even if you do that
in the US, they're still the rest of the
world. And so what what does that mean
to the rest of the world? like if we
disable them like if we make them
illegal in the US then you still give
the ability for everyone in the else in
the world to use that for malicious
reasons and then you again to back the
argument what happened at uh hugging
face and open AI like you can't then
defend yourselves because the model that
you have from them does not let you
defend yourself so that's actually a
worse position to be in right so I mean
narratives depending on whatever
narratives are out there is about the
incentive of the person that is saying
those narratives and of course some of
us here have very much incentives to say
that open is good because we have
monetary incentives to do that. But even
outside of that, when you look look at
it really closely, you can't um make
that illegal for the entire world, which
means you're putting the US at a, you
know, inferior position to defend
himself, which I think is a bad thing to
do.
>> How do we get out of this?
>> I don't think we get out of it. Uh I
think that this is just an ongoing, you
know, everything right now is polarized.
everything's politicized. Everyone has
two uh uh views of that. And so that
will continue to be the case. But I very
much one think that the um closed source
will continue, the frontier will
continue um but open source will be
there and it will enable people to do a
lot of things both to what you said like
dual use like you can't stop it from
being good and bad. It is what it is and
so we as a society now will have to or
as enterprises will have to protect
ourselves from within. So you have to
protect yourselves internally um so that
your models don't do something bad
malicious internally or go externally
and you will have to defend yourself
from outward from other malicious
actors. The analogy I have is like if
you were a bank three years ago before
or five years ago, right? You still had
to protect yourself from employees
internally
>> um to stop doing malicious things and
from people actually externally stealing
money from the bank. Like that is what
every enterprise will have to do in the
sense of models from a security
perspective.
>> I I might add something that like
I'm very pro- open but that doesn't mean
I'm anti-closed.
>> Yeah.
>> And I think both solutions have a place
to play in the market. let consumers
decide what they prefer to use, but that
competition
helps keep, you know, prices in check.
Like I I don't want to spend $300 per
million output tokens, right?
>> Um the open models help drive down the
cost of the, you know, the primary two
closed labs, right? And so, um and and
obviously, you know, to your point is
that there's a lot of benefits to using
these open models. they don't have they
won't refuse to do certain tasks, right?
Um and and obviously by consequence
maybe that means they can do things that
may not be ideal, right? But it's
incumbent upon anyone that's hosting
these models uh to put in their own
guard rails to ensure that there is, you
know, not necessarily the host like
inference providers, but moreover if
you're providing the service to your
enterprise customers or or you know, to
your downstream consumers. um to to have
your own guard rails in place, right?
Like there's it's not that everything
has to be baked into the parameters of
the model.
>> You have a lot of you know great tools
like classifiers and ACL and things that
you can stitch into your network. You
can you know uh improve your harness and
and and other areas of this. So I think
at the end of the day consumers will
decide what they want. I don't think the
narrative that uh closed open models are
inherently unsafe is is consistent with
popular belief. Um but it helps for
certain interests, right?
>> Well, Dimma, talk a little bit about the
guardrails. I mean, is is that part of
what you do?
>> Yeah. Yeah. I mean, I think for
guardrails, it's like uh it's much more
important to focus on like applications
than on core technology. And I mean
specifically for cyber security I think
it's really really like it's dual use
and it's also really hard to define like
what the right cartils are right we
actually been running like closource
open source models uh on like various
cyber security benchmarks and it's funny
because
>> like current open source models do much
better than the frontier because
Frontier just refuses to run the
benchmark even if benchmark has
explicitly prompted like hey I am
patching my codebase I want to find gaps
etc. kind of uh echoes the experience of
this hiding face open AI stuff. So I
think it's specifically for cyber
security it's so hard to find and the ex
exit decision boundary at the general
model API level
>> and I think it's more important to kind
of move this regulations etc on like
there are other bottlenecks for like
potentially dangerous products you know
especially if you're going more into
physical world where you can enforce
security and enforce better guard rails
I think for cyber security it's just
historically been very hard uh because
attack and defense look so similar and
that's why the best way to secure the
environment. What we learned from you
know previous cryptography regulations
right like or Linux or whatever is that
the best way is to actually enable wider
community to be able to defend
themselves and that's the best way to
prevent attackers not try to constrain
constraint the technology itself. I
think for other potentially dangerous
domains there's there are more kind of
physical world bottlenecks where it's
maybe more practical.
>> Can I ask a question on this? I'm just
curious I don't want to put you on top
spot. I'm just curious on the liability
segment where like I assume the closed
source you can't do a lot of things
because I assume they are legally or
potentially can be liable if it does
something wrong right um and so if I
post train my own model and then I run
it like I would be liable if I run it
myself but if you guys run it do you
guys being like do you guys worry about
that at all like putting in regard Rails
on top of that or is it the liability of
the person that created the
>> I mean I think fundamentally it's like
who who are you using as a as a final
application like that's that's going to
be reliable. I mean to taking your
analogy right like if you if you're AWS
and you run you know like run malicious
code I mean like yeah they I mean if
it's some large scale operation they're
going to cooperate with the government
etc. Of course, they're going to shut it
down, etc. But AWS is not going to audit
every single Docker container you
upload, whether it has malicious code or
not. And I think that's the reasonable
practice for like infrastructure
providers, right?
>> You can't put this kind of job of
regulation without attaching to the
application
>> in some sense.
>> Well, Matt, you said you are pro- open
but not anti-closed. And isn't that sort
of what uh Daario from Anthropic said
this week that he's pro closed but not
anti-open like not the same thing but
the opposite the correlary. So I'm just
wondering is this the biggest I mean is
this is are journalists like me just
blowing this up or in the industry is
this something you're actually afraid of
happening? I I think the narrative has
changed, right? Two weeks ago it was
closed is inherently insecure and now
it's we're at the frontier and the
frontier is insecure, right? And so by
consequence, anything that's open would
also be insecure. Anything that's closed
is insecure, but at least closed. We can
be good stewards and and protect the
world, right?
um the the narrative has just changed
but ultimately the underlying message is
still there which is that open is
inherently insecure and and again it's a
very old message it you know we it it's
there's just no no basis to it right I
think the the only consideration and I
think a lot of researchers are thinking
about this which is that if they hit
some frontier level capability
that could put you know the world in
jeopardy or uh infrastructure structure
in into jeopardy. These sort of things
that there has to be special
consideration and I think this is what a
lot of folks are starting to talk about
now. uh Demis sort of proposed around
having some group to make a decision
about whether something is frontier
level and whether it should be gay
gatekept right um which I don't know if
that is the you know how thick that
regulation becomes but uh certainly it's
incumbent upon all the labs to
be good stewards and and make decisions
about what they feel like they should
release but I will promise you you know
the safety testing that happens in the
US is pretty rigorous. It takes, you
know, quite some time. Um, and it delays
model launches, but it's it's fairly
rigorous. The in China, they don't have
that same rigor, right? the models are
shipped
>> post training like it's it's being ready
to ship and so um
that you know get that question around
like you know competition and and these
sort of things um at this at sort of
sacrificing safety for that right and I
don't know that every country is going
to align across this you know idea of
being good shepherds or good stewards of
of model releases
>> ju just to add to that but but whether
it's open or closed. What we've
experienced in the past month with all
the vulnerabilities has nothing to do
with the model.
>> Okay? It could have happened to an open
model actually happened to closed
models.
>> I think it's it just shows these models
are getting smarter and smarter. There's
no doubt about that. Whether it's open
or closed,
>> it's it's what's around the model. It's
the agent applications.
It's the harness. It's the containment
where they have to catch up with that
sophistication. So I think no matter
where this ends up, I think there will
be a space for both open and closed. We
still are accountable when we build
applications and ship them to customers.
Whichever the models we use is to ensure
that the containment layers and ensure
that the guard rails ensure that there's
a human in the loop for key decisions to
ensure that there is a gateway. We don't
know whether uh Enthropic was was
Enthropic using a gateway or not because
usually if you're using a gateway, you
would not allow an agent uh to go and
talk to the outside world without a
gateway. So there's
>> Yeah, open had like a proxy that had
like a day zero exploit, right?
>> Um but that's a good point around the
harnesses like that's what's it's not
just the model that's driving it. The
harness is very much driving it too. I
have a theory that some of the new
models are being trained on traces that
are intentionally
um looking for ways to exploit systems
uh to give them that capability. And so
also, you know, it's just not an
emergent property. It's actually like
>> uh part of the RL process.
>> Sure. One thing to add on that which was
interesting that didn't happen which you
would assume that um you can use that
same agent or harness with or agent like
model or the harness together to try to
see if there's a zero day exploit before
you give it the task that can use the
zero day exploit right like you could do
that as well and sort of find that out
>> and to your point about harnesses and
monitoring I mean you can I mean you can
ask similarly capable model of like to
give it a task of monitoring the traces
and see what's going on
>> it's perfectly observable able, right?
We just like good best practices how to
build secure systems.
>> Agree. I I think two 3 weeks from now,
we're not going to be having this
conversation about open versus closed
weights. I think we're going to be
talking about harnesses.
>> Um it's just this this field is moving
so fast. It's just there's a new thing
every day.
>> Yeah. And I think one thing you said
about the human in the loop. I want to
challenge that because in both the open
AI hugging face um and the you know
anthropic models having accidentally
been given internet access those were
both human errors right like those it
wasn't like
it wasn't the fault of the agent it was
the fault of the humans and we hear all
the time that you know agents are
getting smarter they're getting smarter
than us like are we seeing a world you
know we want to bring out harnesses but
will will agents be holding the harness
next year when we're at this conference
>> [laughter]
>> Who wants to take this one?
>> Well, I could add to like um to give
some like credit to Dawn. Uh it the
model was running against exploit gym,
right? To try and test cyber
capabilities, right? and and it found a
day zero bug and the proxy proxy was its
only um ability to reach the internet
>> and uh and but that's the harness is
running it. It's trying to do exploits.
That's very intentional about what it's
what the model's intent is at that
point.
>> Um but I'm yeah that's not the answer to
the question but I just wanted to add
some color. I mean I mean I think even
even if harness will be like more
automated mean you still have like
initial design and initial kind of
metatask loop whatever you call it
design I think that responsibility of
doing this responsibly still lays on
application or human etc and this is
like not something new I mean like
models are really good at reward hiking
right I mean I mean we were doing like
pytor know GPU mode all those like
competitions for writing kernels for in
CUDA using models And like it's
incredible like what kind of ways they
find how to cheat against that hardness
until you close all possible deaths.
It's just it's just amazing because yeah
you just burn you burn comput you burn
intelligence to find the answer and
whatever way leads to that there but it
is possible to close to close all the
gaps and you can use the superior
intelligence you can use models to close
those gaps. So I think it's in my mind
it's not that different than you know
like open internet cyber security
discussions from before. The difference
is just scale and speed of iteration
like suddenly went 10x or 100x faster
because there is no human in the loop in
many cases
>> but it's still possible and doable like
similarly how we figured out you know
processes for patching vulnerabilities
and rolling out etc. like yeah those
proxies need to upgrade.
>> Uh a lot of this can be improved. have
very good models to help us with that
but fundamentally like it still can be a
balanced and functioning ecosystem.
>> Yeah. So basically it's going to be a
good year for the security companies
because we just have to invest more
again to your point like about um scale
and speed of these attacks and just on
the defense side we have to equalize
that and then we're should get to a
equilibrium with that. [snorts]
>> Did you have something you wanted to
add?
>> Um I mean listen we build agent systems
they're incentivized to solve a problem.
we tell it to solve a problem. What
happened with hugging face and open AI?
They were told to go, the agent was told
to go and do a benchmark and solve that.
And the agent did exactly that and they
found loopholes in the system to to
solve what they're trying to do. There
will be many of those in the future. I I
don't think we could say that if we
solve this one, there's no 20 others
coming the next month. And I think we
need to build these systems with the
right guard rails and gateways and human
in the loop so that we can um address
unanticipated threats whether they are
cyber security threats. In this case it
wasn't a cyber security threat. It was a
you know it was the agent finding
loopholes in the system. Both of these
are are critical. There was I think a
couple months ago three months ago AWS
the Kira one too uh same thing. it was
an injection into the prompt. So these
things could happen because of the agent
doing that or it could be a threat from
the outside. We have to build these
system to be resilient
to these unanticipated uh
vulnerabilities.
>> The biggest thing though is like every I
I believe that every company will be
hacked in the next 12 months like every
single one. Like you only the we were
talking about this internally the other
day is whereas like the only reason you
might not get hacked is luck.
>> Like luck you just weren't you weren't a
target. I mean because in the sense that
it could be like the hugging face. No
one wanted to get you hacked but they
did hack you. So what do we do in the
meantime with all the data that will be
hacked and everything will come out like
we will obviously at some point in time
get to the counterbalance but till that
point in time you should assume that
every company will be will be hacked in
some form until then and so that's the
scarier part.
>> Yeah.
>> It happens without agents already.
>> Exactly. Exactly. [laughter] Yeah.
>> So we've talked a lot about security.
What about re reliability or um cost
like you know how how are you thinking
about um this new conversation around
just finding models that are cheaper to
run.
>> How many people have actually I'm
interested in the audience. How many
people have fine-tuned models? Just
raise your hands.
>> Wow. More than I expected. [laughter]
I I think generally is um you fine-tune
a it's expensive to fine-tune a model at
scale. Okay, I work for Google and to
finetune a model it takes a lot of a lot
of money. Okay, to do that compute and
people um you do that for a reason
you're trying to build something that is
for a specific change of behavior for a
specific sectors uh telos are doing that
today. They need that because they need
model to understand the telco business,
the jarens, the behavior of the telco
industry. But I think generally context
is does 90% of the job. It's
transparent. You see what you're giving
it. You could change it almost every
day, every week. Um I'm a big advocate
of context. I think only few times where
a fine tuning is actually required.
>> I have a bit of contrarian view. I I
think I'm more bullish on the domain
specific and task specific models that
aren't over parameterized and um you
know I I don't need 2.8 trillion
parameters if all I'm doing is like some
like heavy document processing and
parsing and things like this, right? And
like QA and whatever. um the
you can load up context but I think
ultimately um if you've fine-tuned and
did some like RL for your models there's
like real value in pulling in sort of
that domain specific knowledge from your
own enterprise to be able to make that
model more efficient for yourself and
your inference costs just go right down
right when you're we're talking like you
know something in the 20 billion
parameter range or you know not you know
trillion plus whatever.
>> I mean, it's interesting you mentioned
90%. I I mean, I I would agree with
that, but it's like 90% of quality,
right? And I think if you're starting to
build some use case or you're trying to
prototype an application, like sure,
load up the context, that's that's the
simplest,
>> but once you actually get some data
flowing through your product,
>> yeah,
>> uh the equation changes. Yeah. And if
it's like AI native startup once you
once you scaled up you see that people
are reaching out for fine tuning for RL
to
>> basically specialize in build
fundamentally a better product because
they have the user data
>> there are a lot of traditional
enterprises which are kind of waking up
to the fact that they actually have this
decades of internal processes internal
data
>> which actually what makes their company
that special right and they want to
leverage that and there's there are
limits how You can short it in the
context.
>> I agree with that. There are also limits
how much they want to collaborate
collaborate to contribute this
information to a general model which
everybody uses diluting their advantage
and those are kind of
>> kind of
>> control of kind of workflows and unique
advantage and just driving
>> better user experience and cost are like
main factors which we see
>> we see driving this and yeah people
start with context but they kind of once
they get usage once they get data fl
they reach out for like specialized
intelligence and we see it with our
customers That's a lot of like digital
native AI native companies and like some
enterprises are also like
>> we've also
>> waking up to that
>> we also see on that in the sense of
continual learning where people are like
not only not only the historical data
but like every single day or week
whatever you take all the new data from
the usage and you essentially the
argument of is of some of our customers
which are these startups is that you'll
get better than frontier performance on
what you're trying to achieve.
>> Exactly. because it's like
>> for vertically specialized type of
>> but I mean I mean also it's important to
keep in mind like Frontier Labs are
doing the same thing right like there's
a reason why cloud codeex exists right
it's effectively a data collection
engine to make the models better
>> they are totally fine tuning models for
the best usage with their products
>> so if we want to kind of have level
playing field for everyone it makes
sense to kind of enable every business
to be able to do that
>> yes
>> it might not be something which you
reach out immediately for I mean of
course if you're prototyping do
something simple but this is the core
advantage I think for any product and
any business so I would bet that you
know big part of future use cases
especially at scale will will be
customized specialized customized
intelligence both from primarily from
quality side and as a nice benefit also
much lower cost because you don't need
the whole fable size model in order to
solve some more narrow use case
>> and I think we get caught up in this
idea that the world is just like it's
the model that's giving all the mileage,
right? like and then okay harness like
you know self-improving harnesses and
it's really cool but there's a lot of
other things that you put into an
organization in an enterprise right like
I mean
many enterprises aren't even using
prompt caching like they're just
throwing money into the bucket um
>> because they don't have like the proper
architectures deployed and so there's a
lot of opportunity for like model
routing and prompt caching and other
things that can help you know tune the
overall machine right and got to move
away from like the model thinking to
like systems thinking, right? Like real
like systems design.
>> Um I'd love to end I think the world
works mostly by fear. So I'd love to end
with the question what keeps you up at
night. Start with you Mazin in ter in
terms of agentic development the future.
>> Um I think um the unknown.
Uh there's a lot of we're still very
early in this in this game and I think
there's a lot that we don't know about
and these agents can certainly be
extremely powerful in doing a lot of
damage if they're not built right and um
so what's around the model not the model
keeps me up at night all the time.
I mean I guess we we talked about open
and close right I mean those that's a
kind of an an example how rapidly
changing technology can lead to like
societal policy changes which are may
may or may not be well thought through.
So I think the yeah given night that you
know the way like society or policy
reacts to emerging technology ends up
being like very damaging to society
[snorts] itself or like to development
of technology and basically we we as
organizations do something very very
dumb right and we're going to regret it
later and yeah
trying to avoid that is what keeps me up
at night
>> so so that I don't repeat anything
that's already been said because Those
certainly do keep me up at night. Um I'm
actually concerned about like
disinformation campaigns at scale. So if
you can command a huge number of agents,
you know, in one person like there's
it's very popular idea especially in
China like of a oneperson company,
right? Being able to like scale yourself
in infinitely here. Um not as popular
here but like it's you know still talked
about. But if you can if you're
weaponizing agents like one person can
cause serious damage. If you have a
nation state behind that, they can cause
major damage, right? And so we already
suffer from this at certain scale, but
being able to scale that up uh you know
can be particularly dangerous.
>> Yeah, you left me with nothing like
[laughter]
everything. I'll just throw like a you
know one render out there is um outside
of the all these things which are
obviously true is like um the the
general models or technologies that we
use are like there's very much unknown
but directionally known where they're
going and so like the fear is like are
there a net new type of technology
models coming out that actually re that
change everything that we already quote
unquote know and not know then that just
entirely changes the fears and the
landscape and everything like that. So
that is a worry and it's not a you know
uh non it's a very non-zero chance that
it happens. So yeah
>> the nonzero chance.
>> Yeah.
>> Well thank you so much. We're out of
time. Thank you so much for your time
for listening. Thank you to our
panelists because I sent them probably
three dozen questions and maybe asked
one of them. So [laughter] thank you.
I'm here to host the session on AI
agents in finance and legal. So, how do
you use the uh the uh things that we
were just talking about on stage, these
agents, which uh we know have some
concerns about how you use them in these
high high uh risk domains like legal and
finance. Uh by way of background, I'm an
investor at Mayfield Fund. We are 57y
old venture fund. We're investing out of
funds 19 and 20 uh based here in the Bay
Area. Um we've invested over 700
companies in the history of the fund. Of
those 125 have gone public, 250 have
been acquired. Um, we take a very people
first approach to building companies. We
realize it's entrepreneurs that build
companies and there will be a lot of ups
and downs that company building is a
marathon not a sprint and we've seen a
lot of the ups and downs and so we don't
panic when those things happen. Uh,
we're very focused on the entrepreneurs
because we know the entrepreneurs are
the ones that really build the companies
and make that happen. We invest anywhere
from seed and inception all the way up
to series B and we go up and down the
stack all the way from infra. So it
could be semis optics switching models
uh to infrastructure software to cyber
cloud dev tools all the way up to the
application layer. Um we're going to
have a series of three talks and then a
panel all on this topic of using AI
agents and legal and finance. Uh first I
want to introduce uh Milinda Nafed. He
is the SVP of AI foundations at Capital
One. Um he leads a team building
generative AI and agentic AI across the
bank. He joined Capital One in May 2023
after 25 uh years of applying AI to
solve business and scientific
challenges. Most recently, he was CTO of
Metropolis at NVIDIA and he had earlier
stints with Cisco and IBM and he holds a
PhD uh as well. So, please help me
welcome Milind. Thank you.
>> Thank you.
Uh good afternoon folks. Um I know this
is one of the last sessions between you
and the end of the week so I'll try to
keep it brief. Um I'm Milan Naft. Um I
run all of the AI research and
development at Capital One. Um
trying to go to the next slide.
So, Capital One is um always been it has
always been a technology uh leader,
technology first company and the belief
is that the the winner of this in
banking is going to be a technology
company that has deep technology roots
as well as deep understanding of you
know how to manage risk well. Um we have
been on a journey um uh on of technology
transformation for a while now. the
first large bank on the public cloud. Um
a modern data ecosystem and a deeprooted
uh you know respect for datadriven
analysis from our very origins and along
uh journey in terms of applying machine
learning and artificial intelligence um
to the problems uh to solve uh that our
customers can benefit from. Um recently
uh over the last three and a half years
we have actually put significant
investments in um generative AI and
agentic AI and we are among the first uh
to enterprise to actually launch agentic
AI into production you know a couple of
years ago. I'll talk more about that in
a minute.
The way we think of ourselves is uh we
want to use um science [snorts]
uh and first principles to affect change
across all the layers of the AI stack
that end up helping Capital One's
customers and help help us enrich all
our experiences. To do that we have
built this organization called AI
foundations which is predominantly uh AI
researchers, applied AI engineers, uh
data scientists and and so on and so
forth. And we try to actually achieve
business impact through scientific uh
innovation and pushing the frontiers of
uh AI uh and the state-of-the-art AI. So
to that effect you know we have more
than 65 publications in leading um
research conferences and and journals
this year. Uh this number keeps growing.
We are a very big part of uh you know
some of the conferences that I'm sure
you guys all attend whether it's ICML
ICLR neurips um ACM u so on and so
forth. uh we are also uh very uh closely
partnering with academia and industry.
We have various partnerships with uh
University of Southern California,
University of Illinois at Arbana
Champagne, Colombia University um and
and a few others uh [snorts] where we
work closely with the researchers uh in
advancing safe AI. Um so that's one of
the things that we do. um in terms of
our belief that true differentiation
only comes you know from customizing the
entire AI stack with our data and
Capital 1's AI advantage is Capital 1's
data advantage you know being converted
into an AI advantage through our
scientific uh work of customizing this
tech here are just a few papers that
that we just published you know one of
them is from new um where we talk about
how to generate
data sets, curated data sets for
multi-turn conversations in
multi-agentic environments, which is a
very different problem than synthetic
data generation for a single turn or
single agent uh interactions. We have
some work on you know how to route uh
generated data uh through multiple
models. You can think of this as a
mixture of models instead of mixture of
experts. That's some of the work that we
presented at ACL. and then something
recently at ICML on criticguided
distillation [snorts] for uh robust
reasoning all these are just samples of
our work there's a lot more where this
comes from u and given that I have very
limited time I just want to say this
capital one was at the forefront of
agentic AI you know we started our
agentic AI exploration more than two and
a half years ago and we actually had our
first production system uh using
multi-agentic AI very early last January
and while there are a lot of innovations
that we have worked on the overall
framework what we call maca um comprises
of four different agents or four
different class of agents one is an
understanding agent that either
interacts with the environment or with
the customers and tries to figure out
what is it that they need one is a
planner agent that actually has access
to all of the APIs and all the knowledge
and all the policies of Capital One so
it can figure out how to satisfy that
need. And you know some of the secret
sauce is in the evaluator agent which is
um a completely independent agent that
validates the plan you know figures out
using a world model a very simple world
model whether executing that plan uh
will fit capital one policies and and
will be safe to do and if not you know
it can kick it back to the planner agent
which can in turn kick back uh to the
understanding agent for enhanced uh
input needed from the customer. So this
is a non-deterministic system at play
naturally and so this is not something
that is just you know uh this is not uh
our you know this is not robotic um just
done differently with agents. This is an
inherently non-deterministic system of
agents that works together to achieve
outcomes. And finally we have an
explainer agent that will talk in you
know what humans can understand in uh
the rest of the agents talk in their own
language. Of course, we have been
working on this as I said for more than
two and a half years and we have some of
the examples of this working in
production. So when any of you um is is
trying to buy an automobile um using a
bunch of dealerships throughout the
country that use Capital One on the back
end, you're most likely interacting with
our chat concier that helps you figure
out, you know, what you are looking for
in the vehicle, availability,
appointments, [snorts] uh if you want to
trade in a vehicle, you know, all those
things 24/7 365 fully autonomously.
There's another use case that we debuted
last year which is helping our consumer
bank um on fraud related uh
conversations with the customers. So
part of this is understanding the the
customer's complaints. Part of this is
recommending the right set of actions
for our agents to take and then of
course the last part is summarizing the
conversation so that we create a
learning corpus for us for uh the next
set of interactions.
Um I would just like to say that u we
have uh been growing uh dramatically
because we believe as I said in first
principles research we are advancing the
state-of-the-art wherever we need to. Um
as I said we are working at all layers
of the stack. So we are working on
customizing the foundational models
themselves. We are customizing the
services that go along with them with
our data. We are customizing at the
agentic layer of of the AI stack and of
course we are working with all parts of
Capital One in implementing solutions
that leverage this. So even at the
solution layer and so to do that you
know these are the three job families
that we hire. We are hiring for those of
you who may know someone or may be
interested in coming and you know
changing banking for the good in working
on AI going from research into
production in record time know that's
typically unheard of in regulated
enterprises um and for those of you who
want to see 130 million customers
leverage your work you know um learn
from it and create that continuous
learning loop Please you know contact us
and we would be happy to talk to you
about the various positions we have open
to fill. Thank you.
Thank you so much.
Awesome. Our next speaker is Nikquille
Chanduk. Uh Nquille is the chief product
officer at Circle where he leads product
technology and AI strategy for the
company behind USDC. Before circle,
Nquille led product or augmented reality
glasses at Meta uh and launching the
company smart glass and Spark AR studio.
Early in career he ran product at
YouTube uh and turning turning YouTube
music profitable and launching the first
YouTube app on iPhone. Uh he is also a
graduate of the Ohio State University.
Go Bucks. Uh, please help me welcome to
Keel.
>> All right. Uh, thank you for the kind
introduction. I know it's late, so I'll
I'll also be quick. Uh, this is the last
slide. Yeah.
Uh, that's one way to get me out of
here. Uh, all right. So, I work at a
company called Circle. Circle is a
stable coin issuer. Uh for a lot of
people who don't know stable coins,
stable coins is a new type of money that
exists in the world. Uh its roots are in
crypto as in like traditionally
understood as like you know bitcoin or
ethereum or whatever that is. But as of
June last year it is real uh it is real.
A law was passed in the United States
called the genius act. And the genius
act made it so that anybody you can
transact with stable coins just like you
transact with money. Okay. And that law
goes it goes through 18 18 months of
rule making. Rulem ends like end of this
year. By next year, Genius is live.
Stable coins are real money that real
companies and like real people can use
to do uh things much like they do with
bank money or like any other money that
they have. So I want to set that
background so so people understand like
why I am here. So we're going to talk
about like building infrastructure for
the agentic economy. know that like as
we talk about that sort of my roots are
in like the onchain like uh blockchain
ecosystem from which like USDC came out
and and now USDC is legal tender in the
United States hopefully by next year.
Okay. So um a lot of the discussion
today has been about like agents uh
agent governance uh and like making sure
that agents are secure but a lot of that
discussion is inward facing and one of
the things that USDC does is it lives on
the public internet. It is uh open money
that lives on the public internet like
an a user who and the typical user of
USDC today but changing changing uh
rapidly is somebody who doesn't have
access to dollar banking rails right so
if you live in the United States there
are 330 million of us uh a lot of us
have access to good banking and it is it
is very easy for us to go get like a
dollar bank account and like get access
to uh get access to uh dollar payment
methods if you live across the world and
there are like like you know 8 billion
people around the world uh six billion
of them have a phone and they they don't
really have a way of like transacting
with dollars okay and so what USDC uh
did first was was made it possible for
all of those people to start interacting
with dollars okay so those dollars live
on the public internet they don't live
inside a bank they're just onchain you
can see the transactions on chain agents
similarly today like much like money
that lives sort of inside is are going
to turn outward boards. That's our bet.
Our bet is like agents are going to be
like endpoints are going to be endpoints
on the internet much like websites are
endpoints on the internet and we are
going to be racing to build these new
agents uh as soon as we get the tech
right. So I'm analogizing it with FSD.
uh FSD like the way to think about it is
like hey FSD was designed with the
assumption that the roads are not going
to change but like what if you could
design with the assumptions that you
could actually redo the entire uh
transportation system you could redo the
entire highway system that's how we
think about uh that's what we think
about when we think about using agents
in USDC
so here are some examples agents don't
tap to pay like this is a common
modality like you go out you uh tap to
pay uh agents don't have a way of doing
that Uh, next slide.
Uh, agents can plug into existing
financial rails. So, you can give your
agent your credit card. You can say
like, "Hey, go spend money with my
credit card." Now, imagine a world in
which your agent spawns a 100 sub
agents, okay? And each one of them need
value and like each one of them need
governance and each one of those each
one of those actions by those sub agents
need to be programmable. It's not
possible to do with like existing
payment rates. Okay. So a lot of the
things that actually exist in the world
in in in commerce and even in systems
like sophisticated systems like Android
and otherwise are built around like what
payments can enable and not enable. And
what stable coins do is they give you
the ability to have uh programmable
money where you can assign like logic to
it and you can do it without requiring
the agent to have a bank account without
requiring the agent to have a credit
card. So if my agent spawns another 100
agents which then spawn another 100
agents, each one of them can have a US
can have a wallet. They can have a
onchain wallet. They can have rules that
govern that wallet and you can actually
do all of the tracking out in the open.
So
um so what are some of the other
assumptions we've made? So in both
traditional payment systems and in like
onchain systems, uh there's this concept
of finality, right? What does it mean
when finality is when I have paid you
money and that transaction is final.
Okay, that is a pretty important that is
a very important consideration like when
you do an a uh when you do a uh payment
like when an agent swipes a credit card
the merchant is only going to get the
money like after the issuer bank has
cleared the funds. So it is not full
finality. It's a really important
concept when you send money on an
onchain in in an uh in onchain. You want
to make sure that like there is absolute
finality for like when when the money
has moved from like wallet one to wallet
two. So probabilistic finality
essentially compounds the risk in the
system. If you have multiple agents and
if you have if you're imagining a future
which there are millions and millions of
agents or there are more agents than
there are humans which is true for web
pages and websites today on the
internet. You cannot have probabilistic
finality.
Uh also so far a lot of like the
blockchain payments happen out in the
open there. They happen using a public
ledger which is great for auditability
but is not great to do real economic
value. If my wallet is fully public on
chain and you can see how much how many
balance how much balance I have. It's
very hard for me to actually do real
economic activity because I would be
leaking out too much information. So
uh we assume trust can be at the
application layer at like at agent scale
at agent scale it is really really
difficult. Okay each assumption breaks
for a reason like every assumption in
the current payment system and payment
system essentially which moves all of
the values assumes that the human is one
step away is always ready there is
present for governance.
Okay what is the way to fix this? We
believe there's a way to do this which
is open architecture uh which is to make
sure that like all of these agents are
running on open systems. They are able
to interact with uh they're able to
interact with other agents on these open
systems. Payments for payments for these
interactions are happening in not just
our stable coin but in any stable coin
that is available in the market and it
is open by design and open by necessity
because that's how the web evolved. The
web evolved from like a few N&TP and FTP
servers back in the early 90s for those
who remember to what is now an
innumerable number of uh uh websites and
web pages in the world. Okay, so this is
what we're doing. We're doing it at
agentscircle.com. We have a CLI. Please
try it out. Uh it's a marketplace of uh
task based activity that you can do. Uh
you can do payments as low as a
millionth of a cent uh to actually get a
task done. Uh people are trying
different kinds of tasks. Everything
from go infer this for me to go do this
research or go write this piece of code
for me and all of this all of this all
of this is designed to be operated by
agents for agents and off agents. Okay,
thank you.
And now I'd like to introduce our final
speaker and then we'll have a panel
panel following that Faraj Shafi. He is
the head of product and solutions at
Wells Fargo uh where he oversees a
vision roadmap for AI powered products
across the bank. He joined Wells after
more than 15 years in technology
leadership at AWS, Verizon, AT&T and
Google. Um and he first stepped in his
first experience in AI and data was back
in 2016 when he joined Verizon as chief
data and chief AI officer. So please
help me welcome Faraz.
Good afternoon everyone.
It's an absolute pleasure being here. My
name is Faras Shafi. I lead products and
solutions for Wells Fargo.
We've largely lived in a world that has
been defined by what we call cognitive
scarcity. So think before AI, even
though it's very hard to think before
AI, but think before November 2022.
If you needed to build a mobile app, you
needed to hire people, hire
organizations that had the special skill
set to build a mobile app. Just like
that, before you needed to build a
website, you needed specialized skills,
specialized teams to build a website.
What's different about AI is that we are
now in the world defined by cognitive
abundance
where intelligence is not the issue
anymore. You want to build a mobile app,
it's as easy as going on cloud or chat
GPT or tens of others applications and
literally describing what you want. And
so we believe that we've really entered
into this very new paradigm and a very
new interesting era.
Now banking has been around for a long
time. It's been it's hundreds of years
old. But the first time we actually saw
physical ATMs come into the picture in
the US was roughly 1960s. So that's the
first time we actually saw physical ATMs
come in. And so you could actually now
go into an ATM, not go into in in the
bank, but actually just go to the ATM if
you just wanted cash. Then about 1980s
is when telephonies started to come in
and if you could make a simple change
via the phone, you would just call in
like I want to update my address. I want
to do some balance transfer or just know
where is the status of the credit card
that was shipped. So what happened is
now people started using phones for the
use cases where phone was a good use
case and then 2000s with the internet
era we saw a big emergence where people
started using the web. So now you open
your laptop, you log in, you can take a
look into your account and you can do
many many things on the web. And then
eventually 2010s, thanks to the iPhone
and app store and I guarantee everyone
in this room has at least one banking
app if not 10. And so
every time there was a transition,
there's a big shift. In the 1960s, ATMs
was the only choice. So 100% people
would go to the ATM or the bank. When
telephone came in, some people would
start going on that route. Use a phone.
Others would still continue to go to an
ATM or a bank. Same with web. The stuff
that you can do online, you'll do
online. The stuff that you still have to
go to a bank, you would go in. And so we
believe that this year has been the
beginning of another era where the
interface is being redesigned and
refined and we believe that the banking
experience is actually going to start
within the agent
and so now it's about people asking
going on claude or chat GPT and asking
what should I do about my 529 college
plan or hey I just have this new job
it's asking me to relocate to a certain
place what would be the best way to do
that and so we're seeing this massive
shift where the information or the
intelligence and specifically the user
interface is actually becoming the agent
to a fact where we potentially believe
that the future you may not need an app
anymore because you have an agent that
takes care of that. And so we do believe
that this is the start of a massive and
a new era in the world of AI.
And again, it's not just a demo or a
proof point, but it is an actual working
use case. So for Wells Fargo, our AI
assistant just crossed uh 1 billion plus
customer interactions.
We have 33 million plus active users on
the platform. And we see that wherever
these tools are being used by our
customers, by our bankers, we saw
roughly 25% higher increase in both the
account openings for deposits as well as
credit cards. So the amount of time that
bankers spend on drafting notes or
looking or researching into client
relationships, most of that now becomes
table stakes. In fact, it just takes a
few minutes and gets that done. And so
again when we say that agents become the
new interface again it's not just
hypothetical it in fact has already
begun.
But one thing that always
challenges [snorts] me and and and the
more I think about this industry is
there's a very small group of companies
and organizations that take majority of
the value created by AI.
So I'm sure many people here would
resonate with these numbers. There's
tons of tons of studies that 10% of the
projects are the the ones that are
successful or 95% of the projects u you
know continue to fail. So we believe
that this is going to continue to be
true for at least the next couple of
years. And the gap is not the model. And
I know there's been a lot of
conversations on models and the models
are unbelievably powerful.
But the model that we're going to use
versus other banks or your organizations
are the same model. We all have access
to Opus 5.0 or Fable or GPT 5.5.
Our model is not any different than the
models that you all will have access to.
So the differentiator is actually not
the model.
The differentiator is the stuff around
the model. How will we use it? Where
will we use it? The how really depends
on things like agentic harnesses, data,
security profile, agents are great, but
when you get them doing a long running
tasks, they actually are not that great.
So that's a problem. If there's
entrepreneurs in the room, please look
into that. That's a huge area.
But the big thing is going to be also
the culture. Also, how do you prioritize
the right use cases? Because one thing I
see all the time is suddenly everything
becomes AI. It doesn't matter what
you're doing. And that's not the right
approach. And so for us, it's a matter
of taking a very phased and systematic
approach.
Wells Fargo is a 174 year old company
[snorts] and we want to be very
meaningful in how we proceed ahead with
AI. So our approach in the short term is
to look at AI as a tool just like you
have your Excel and Word docs and many
other tools. So humans use AI as a tool
largely focused on individual use cases.
So again, you open chat GPT, you're the
one putting in the prompt, getting that
information, and then using that
information to do something.
Then we believe very quickly the world
will move into what we're calling AI as
a teammate.
So now it's less about individual
productivity. It's more about system
workflows. The best example I use is
imagine AI being like a junior employee.
Just like when you hire someone new into
the organization, you need to give them
data. You need to help ramp them up,
give them access to systems. AI would be
exactly the same way. You onboard AI,
you give it the right context, you give
it the information, and more
importantly, you give it feedback
on what is the right way to do things.
So we believe that starting next year
for us our focus will go from AI as a
tool to AI as a teammate. That means
when I think about for example home
lending or a mortgage process which is a
very complex process very human-driven
lot of manual tasks. Now AI as a
teammate means when someone comes in and
submits their mortgage application, the
person can literally just trigger an AI
agent and that AI agent automatically
could basically start looking at
underwriting, look at what's needed,
things like income docs and many other
things. And so AI becomes integrated
into the workflow. It's not sitting
somewhere else. It is not limited to one
person. It is part of the team. In fact,
I believe very quickly we're going to
have AI in the ORC chart. So, we're
going to have home mortgage, the
leadership team, then the product
management, and in every area you're
going to have an AI agent or multiple AI
agents sitting within that. But the end
goal really for us is autonomous AI.
So, in the first two cases, it's largely
still driven by humans. Humans are the
one who are prompting it. Humans are the
one who are defining when it should be
triggered. In autonomous AI, that is
when AI will be telling us what to do
and when to do it. And again, the best
example is just like you have a junior
employee. Imagine you have a senior
employee that has access to the entire
customer database, entirety of the
internet, is very well-versed in your
organization and your processes. they
will be more consistent, more reliable,
and largely more accurate than humans as
well.
Even for humans, by the way, the success
rate that we've seen is 95 to 97%
with consistent processes, this can
easily beat that. And so, in the world
of autonomous AI, you're not waiting for
a trigger like someone came in and
opened a mortgage application. The AI
could literally be sending you a Slack
message saying, "Hey, for us, I saw that
the market rate now is reduced by the
feds. Should we create a new offering
targeted for a certain demographic?" And
my job would ideally be just to say yes
or better yet, it tells me that, hey,
the market rate actually dropped. I
already did the change because I was
99.7%
confident. I've rolled it out and these
are the new things that are already
happening. That is the world of
autonomous AI. And again, my personal
belief is that 2028 onwards will be
defined by this era. This doesn't mean
we're taking a sequential approach. Even
today, we are experimenting with
autonomous AI. But that just means the
mix of things will really start
switching and that's where our focus is
going to be.
And so for us, we want to change
fundamentally how our bank will operate
in this era of AI. We're looking at four
core pillars and those are a core
strategy for us. One is the hub and
spoke model which simply means that
there is not going to be a central team.
The job of the AI organization or an AI
team or the chief AI officer is to now
enable everyone else in the organization
not to be the lone builder. That's what
the hub and spoke models means that you
have to give the tools you have to have
the partnerships the strategy but the
execution should sit within the lines of
businesses. For anyone who's a CIO or
has worked as an IT person, the word
shadow IT is very scary. People get
worried worried about shadow IT. But
there will not be shadow AI because AI
will be for everyone and will be used by
everyone technical or non-technical.
The second thing is to focus on very
clear valuedriven use cases.
Not all use cases are equal and the high
impact use cases will really drive
tremendous value. The third thing is
moving fast. So we are still a bank,
we're still extremely regulated. So we
want to be very safe, very secure. We
want to be we want to take the right
level of risks and so having those
protections is absolutely critical. So
we want to move fast but with a very
disciplined approach. And the final
thing is that to really drive value at
scale, we need our people to be
upskilled and enabled.
You have to drive adoption. But
remember, adoption does not meet impact.
But for impact at scale, you do need
adoption. And so we really want to drive
adoption and impact at scale and upskill
our workforce. And so for the question
for us that defines our strategy is not
what barriers do we have in technology.
In fact we talk about technology very
little because technology is changing a
lot. But our business processes our
challenges and opportunities those are
the real questions. It doesn't matter
what technology comes in two months from
now or three months from now. The
questions we're asking can we do
something better for our customers?
Those questions still remain the same.
And so for us every day we're
challenging if technology is not the
barrier what will we build. Thank you.
Amazing. Thank you for now we have 25 or
so minutes to chat about the use of
agents in legal and finance. So maybe
just to start um
when you think about generic agents uh
may maybe your voice is tired so we'll
we'll start with Nquille. when you think
about agents and applying them to these
uh higher risk areas like finance and
transactions or legal um what are the
difference in requirements between those
agents and and uh agents for other use
cases?
>> Yeah, thank thank you. Um, look, all
finance and legal organizations that I
know of today are already using agents
in some fashion because they're using uh
coding agents. Uh, and and uh coding
agents have this amazing property around
like uh verifiability and testability.
Like you can go in, read the code, you
can decide like if it is if it is too
verbose, not verbose enough, has like
design docs, doesn't have design docs,
all of that stuff like associated with
it. and you have you can run a test
suite against it and make sure that the
uh agent is doing what it's supposed to
be doing. uh with finance and legal I
think um um you can do the same things
but the cost of failure is much higher
right like so I think if we if we are
doing socks compliance or we are getting
earnings ready and we have an agent that
is job is to like get earnings ready um
and I know this because we have earnings
next week um we we cannot take a mistake
like I think like the scrutiny of that
agent like is going to be tremendous uh
and so I think the auditability of the
decision- making that the agent the uh
that the agent is doing uh the kind of
data sources that the agent has access
to uh the verifiability of the of the
output all move up to a really really
really high bar um and and yeah I mean I
think these are one of one of we're
doing this right now like these are one
of the last flows to get automated right
like I think like because because so
much of the company company's existence
depends on its ability to get finances,
right? To make sure that its legal
surface area is like the right
appropriate legal surface area. Uh and
and this is also true in other functions
in like companies like circle like
compliance like we don't want to get
hauled in by regulators just because
like our agent made a mistake. They're
going to hold us responsible not the
agent, right? So
>> makes sense. Thank you.
>> Can I jump on
>> please? Yeah. Yeah.
>> One very important point. So there's I
fully agree with Nikil. There's a
concept called verifiers law. So what
that concept tells you is that tasks
that are easy to verify those are going
to be ripe for agentic processes. So so
imagine sedukco. So sudukco the puzzle
it's hard to do but very easy to verify
right. So anything that's easy to verify
and coding is one of those things where
you do have you know QA and things like
that where you can test it very quickly
but then things that are hard to verify
will be harder to solve and will have a
longer lead time. Self-driving same
thing it's very hard to fully verify
that was the car or the vehicle doing
the right thing at the right time. Same
thing in banking when we have for
example someone come in and submit for a
credit card application or a loan
application some cases we don't have a
lot of data. So if we make an incorrect
decision based on the information we
have and let's just say the person
defaults it may be 5 years from when
they default. So the decision to give
them credit was today. The verification
is 5 years down the road becomes very
hard. And so we do look at the verifi
verification part of it as hey which are
the tasks that are really ripe for
agents that will surpass human call it
you know um probability of being correct
all the time and those would be the ones
that we would always start with.
>> Makes sense. And and I assume that
applies for both in-house agents that
you would build as well as thirdparty
agents that you would buy or do you
treat those any differently whether
they're internally sourced or externally
sourced?
>> I think there's going to be hybrid. The
big thing is that as I sort of mentioned
in my talk as well, the models, the
intelligence is largely going to be the
same. So we we understand that. But then
there's things that for example Wells
Fargo will have in its IP and its data
that others will not. And so there will
be an advantage of having call it
homegrown agents that are doing certain
things. At the same time the the models
and both the call it offtheshelf agents
are becoming so powerful right out of
the box that it just doesn't make sense
to not use them. I think the big thing
will be the economics of them as as soon
as they start coming down they're going
to be more pervasive. Another big thing
that we're looking at is how would the
agents connect to each other? Because
again I I gave the example of a home
mortgage process. It is a very large
very complex roughly 1100step process
that we have in the bank. It will not be
one agent. It's not going to be a
collection of agents that's just
homegrown. It'll be a combination of
many things. And it's not going to be
that this agent does a job really well,
but the other one doesn't because they
need to talk and connect to each other.
Especially when the systems are long
running. You give a prompt, you get a
response back. That's easy. That you'll
be right. But when you want something
done over multiple hours or days or
weeks, the context, that's where it
starts getting a little bit shady.
>> Yeah. And is there is there an approach
or do you know or is it maybe this an
opportunity for entrepreneurs for the
things that take longer that are harder
to verify
any techniques people are using or is
that an opportunity for like hey we made
a decision today but it had an impact
five years later uh but you don't have
that data or you you haven't started to
collect that data. I I would say if if
there's entrepreneurs in the room,
agentic harness for example and it it
the concept sounds so simple, right?
It's a harness that holds everything
together and sits on top of the agent,
but it is incredibly hard to do. Again,
especially for longunning processes. So
that's something that we're actively
looking at. We and the stuff that I'm
talking about are industry specific
problems. These are not just Wells Fargo
problems. The these are industry
specific problems. So anyone who's
focused on for example making the agent
to agent work there's a lot of protocols
out there A2A is a great one a lot of
organizations also are building on top
of standard SDKs so that typically is
not the issue the issue is optimizing
which data to grab for what task. How
would for example a Service Now agent
collaborate with a Salesforce agent,
collaborate with a homegrown agent,
share the right context and the right
information? Very difficult to do. So
that is a big big opportunity.
>> Awesome. And Nquille, when you think
about agents um in your past lines of
work or at Circle, how do you how do you
measure reliability? What are the
metrics that you look at the KPIs and
and how do you determine when an agent
is good enough to put into production or
does that is that variable based on the
on the use case?
>> I mean most definitely varies uh by use
case. There was a discussion I think I
attended this talk today morning it
talked about evals and how eval are
really hard uh and the speaker made this
point that across organizations like
each organization is idiosyncratic on
like evals. I would say within
organizations each team is idiosyncratic
about like evals and so like what to
measure how to measure uh like what is
good like needs to be defined process by
process by process and so like we are
just standing up the frameworks for uh
scalable evals um and then eval break
for all kinds of reasons right like
there can be like model drift there can
be data issues there can be all all
manners of things that that'll that'll
break that'll break uh that'll break how
an agent is performing and so I I would
say like for the places that we have
implemented we have tried to lock down
both the model the harness and like the
amount of variables that are going into
it outside of the input that is coming
in uh and we're we're looking at like uh
we we uh we do evals we also do some of
some of this where we do uh the agent
kind of sits with the human I think it's
called uh some people call it shadowing
and we see we observe like what how the
human's going to do it and we observe
what the agent is going to do it and
that's another I guess that's another
kind of eval if you want to call it that
>> but we do it differently so you're
simultaneously on the job like and
compliance analyst gets an inbound like
they they're making a decision they're
looking at what the agent is doing and
looking at and like and then we sort of
like evaluate that and we sort of run it
in a reinfor in a reinforcement learning
loop so
that's that's sort of like how we're
measuring it the other KPIs we are
trying to figure out is like how much of
like token spend equates to like what
kind of automation we can achieve. And I
think our sort of metrics are really
fussy there. Uh I think it's like right
now we're not focused on like um trying
to save money on the tokens. We're like
letting people use the tokens and seeing
okay well how much sort of productivity
can you achieve? And that productivity
often shows up as like either poor human
more output. That's typically how we're
measuring things. uh and or like you
know in some places it shows up as
revenue like those places are small
still uh or there's some other cost
saving that is obvious or we able to
substitute that that labor that was
doing X to do Y that's another way like
uh KPI show up so it's all of the above
like but yeah it is there's no uh rule
of thumb in saying like well this is how
you do uh KPIs or eval
>> makes sense yeah makes sense uh for us
when you you've talked about the
importance of the harness layer but when
you think about building new agents.
There's, you know, you can look at the
model, you can pick the model, you can
optimize the model, you can build the
harness, you can um look at the
workflow, integrate with the workflow in
different ways, provide different
context, memory. I guess those are all
part of the harness. But when you think
about like that engineering effort, how
do you weight the effort against those
different elements when you're trying to
build an agent?
>> Yeah. I know that that's um that's where
I spent a lot of time because um
think of a traditional product
development life cycle. You would have
an idea. That idea again would go back
and forth into a lot of iterations
typically on a word doc or powerpoint
and then you would engage engineering to
build a Figma, build some type of a you
know prototype
and then it would get into that sort of
development life cycle where again
architectural patterns would come in.
You'd look at vulnerabilities and risk
assessment and things like that. So
again the the traditional development
life cycle is very archaic very
human-driven
very much a call it a sequential process
um in the world of agentic I mean we see
two paths one is the the technical paths
of it which you know as you mentioned
Matt there's like memory the
infrastructure are we going to deploy it
on our cloud or you know work public
cloud or things like that so you have
all these technical choices but a really
key thing are the business choices
because what I tend to see and again
this is maybe another area of
opportunity for the entrepreneurial
folks
today
there's only handful of companies that
are building frontier intelligence
literally handful of companies but
there's going to be a slew of companies
that will be building call it the engine
to make it work in enterprises because
enterprises have many things they need
security, they need governance, they
need compliance. Plus also again going
back to the home mortgage, I don't know
why I'm caught up on the home mortgage
example today, but generally the leaders
would say, okay, we have this large
process. Can you use AI and make it
simpler, faster, better, more automated?
And that is typically the wrong
approach. The approach would be what is
the art of possible using AI and can we
reimagine this whole experience and then
again find a way to go from your current
process to that and I see that as a gap
in the enterprise and I was actually
Nikl and I were talking in the the the
back the green room
when you talk to developers or you know
product managers everyone individually
claims that they are maybe 30% % more
efficient, right? They're writing code
faster than ever before. But for some
cases, you would not see that translate
into workflows. So generally, it would
or it should, but it doesn't always. So
I think that's where the gap is. The gap
is process engineering, understanding
the domain, specific data, understanding
the use cases, and then making sure you
can work backwards into what would be
the right architecture because the
architecture I think is going to
start becoming the easier factor in all
of this.
>> Yeah, sounds like it's uh as most
problems not just technology but people
and process as well. Uh which which is
which can be challenging. I guess next
question would be would be um more
around when you think about the
organizational element and having agents
in the organization. How do you see
that? And and you touched on this
somewhat but but uh curious what you
both think about um you know what does
team composition look like? How do you
think about the ratio of um employees to
agents to to get a certain job done? Um
how does that impact how you think about
building your organizations or evolving
your organizations going forward? You
know, we've I I've seen some companies
that have adopted some agentic
technologies and not necessarily gotten
the benefits versus companies that have
started with a clean sheet of paper and
adopted those technologies because of
the the the legacy that they have and
from a from a organizational perspective
not being able to take advantage of
that. So maybe can Nquille maybe you
first to hear how you how you guys at
Circle think about org design with
agents as a new employee or a new member
of a team.
>> So we're just rolling out the ability
for uh employees to self-publish agents.
Um so we we're in the process of rolling
out like an agent gateway so like you
know what the all all the agents are and
you can like talk to them like you can
find them in Slack and and and connect
with them.
um right now uh the like I don't foresee
a future in which like the um the sort
of like point person on a project is not
a human right like it is going to be a
human like I'm not going to like a human
can then go and like sort of like invoke
all of from one of the many agents we
have inside this company query our agent
gateway figure out like hey who's what
are all the agents available inside the
company like what finance agent do we
have what marketing agent do we have and
compose them into like some kind of
solution. I don't foresee I don't think
about it as an orc design question
because like I don't tell the people
working for me how many Google docs they
can open or how many Google
presentations they can open they can do
whatever they want right like they are
creating an outcome for us so like being
able to self-publish being able to sort
of uh access like data so that you can
self-publish and being able to have like
all the right alles so you can
self-publish and having all the agent
communication figured out that is that
is what I'm focused on like the org
design is like I I don't care like I I I
really think like uh if you have an
agent that can do something then I'm
sure you can do something else for me.
>> Yeah. Yeah. I guess it'll work itself
out. It'll just evolve based on
>> it work itself out. I do think
organizations are will be more
productive which is I think everybody's
experience. uh maybe they will
reorganize because like uh like the
functional sort of uh like a function A
versus function B is like now when the
lines are blurriier and so I do think
like the organizational impact for us is
much more about like well how do we
compose our teams and like you know who
are the people like uh do the product
managers do more product marketing do
the product marketing do more like you
know brand like do like you know do B do
BD do more product like you know there's
all kinds of questions questions like on
sales calls like who's showing up on the
sales calls? You don't need a product
person showing up. Maybe our agent shows
up on the sales calls and gets notes.
So, there's all kinds of efficiencies
like this that are like uh being figured
out, but like yeah, in terms of org
design like old school Mckenzie stuff,
like we're not thinking about it. Makes
sense. Go do what you need to do.
>> Makes sense. And and for us in your in
your role and in your past, what when
you think about adopting agents at
scale, what do you think are the biggest
challenges in organizations to adopting
them at scale? I think the apart from
the technological challenges
I think there's a very interesting um
you know concept that we're starting to
look at which is the fact that there are
not going to be any individual
contributors.
So I don't know how many people in the
room are IC's for the ones that are
working but typically I mean out of our
bank of 200,000 employees largely
they're individual contributors but what
does that mean that means the IC's now
will be manager of agents and so people
that are individual contributors today
they're typically not used to delegating
work they're typically used to owning it
end to end they're fully responsible but
now at this point if you let's just say
get a body of work and you may be you
know using chat GPT or claude or any of
the model then again you still own the
work but you're delegating it and that
is going to be the dominant way of
working moving forwards and so
one thing that we're doing right now is
sort of emphasize
how everyone is going to be a manager
and just like you give feedback to
humans you need to give feedbacks and
have mechanisms to give feedbacks to
your agents to have a way to grow your
agents and get more out of them and and
that's just very new because it is
something that the playbooks really
don't exist. You're not used to a world
of no IC's and all managers. So I just
thought that was a very interesting
snippet that again we're working with
our HR team on on how do we roll that
out. Yeah, it's fascinating and
fascinating and and maybe one more
question for both of you then we'll then
we'll go to uh sort of a final question
but you know there's been all this
discussion in the news the last maybe
three four weeks around um you know
intelligence is becoming democratized
the models are are becoming even the
open source models are getting you know
closer and closer to frontier um but you
as an org that's using this technology
need to think about where is your moat
over time how do you continue to own the
things that differentiate you from your
competitors. So maybe talk about how um
how that impacts how you think about
building product at at at Circle. Um
Nikquille and for you for us at at Wells
Fargo.
>> Yeah. I mean look, we're much smaller
than Wells Fargo.
[laughter] I think um
>> but you have aspirations.
>> Yeah, we have as I think they're two
orders of magnitude like at least in the
engineering organization bigger than us.
Um like look I think of this as uh um
like there's a there's this
I mean there's always a race on right
like you're in a race with somebody and
now suddenly you can wear a jetpack if
you can master the jetpack and you can
take a lead over the over the uh over
the rest of the uh competition. They'll
catch up like they will they will wear
their jetpack and they will get there to
get get there as well. Uh so first I
want to make sure that I put my jetpack
on before and I get my organization to
put on the jetpack before everybody else
does. So like we're very focused on
that. So how do we do that? Uh and
second um uh you're right like you know
a lot of stuff will get commoditized. Uh
I think like software only businesses
like I think there's the I think this is
broad consensus around this. They will
be hard to defend. Uh so we do have some
hard things though like the we are a
company of networks right like we uh
USDC is our core product we think about
it as a stable coin network uh we have a
payments network on top of that which is
we call the circle payments network and
then we're building a new blockchain
which is called arc which is also a
network with because you need validators
and you need participants who are uh
like aligning incentives to participate
in the blockchain so we believe like
these network businesses are superior to
software businesses and software is an
enabler of these network businesses and
how can we sort of like utilize the
software to build these software enabled
networks like essentially um uh which
then also have like a component that is
really difficult like you know like for
some of our ARC blockchain stuff it's
hard computational stuff uh for issuing
a stable coin it's complicated you're
you are chartered by the OC and you have
to submit to the exams and you have to
do all so like the uh like the phys I
almost think about it as the hard
physics of the business and then there's
everything else and the hard physics of
the business. We're very focused on
making sure that we do a really good job
and getting into more businesses that
are adjacencies that are also hard
physics. Uh but and then using this like
accelerant that we have on the top.
>> Awesome. Makes sense.
>> So
I think there's going to be some amazing
changes that we will see for sure in the
banking industry.
>> And many of those things are not
technological challenges by the way like
247 trading. Why does the trading end
at, you know, 400 pm Eastern? Why
doesn't it continue going on? And and
the answer largely is not technological.
It is not a big issue to technologically
enable that. It is that the regulators
want to make sure that the the movement
of money is regulated. They're
protecting the consumers and there's all
these guard rails around that. So you
want to control those those guardrails
just like self-driving is moving at an
incredibly fast pace especially living
here in the Bay Area we witness it
probably more than others
and same thing why is money not let's
just say instantly available anywhere in
the world at a click of a button so a
lot of these there's good technological
solutions but it's more to hey yes I can
make the money available what what if
the other bank is taking two days to
close the book, who's paying for that
delta of two days and what happens when
the money doesn't reach. So, it's all
those other things. So, I think there's
the regulatory part of it which has to
catch up. So, we're going to see some
new use cases as soon as we see better
regulation catch up. And I think Nichol
said it really well that the software
side of it is going to make us do the
hardware side of the business really
well. And when I say hardware, I don't
mean GPUs. I know it's an agentic AI
conference, but you know, we still have
4,000 branches. We still believe that
there's a value in human connection in
having, you know, someone come in and
talk to a bank advisor in Spanish
because they only speak Spanish and and,
you know, build a plan for their
financial education. So, we believe that
those things are not going to go away.
It's just that how they are delivered
and consumed is going to dramatically
change. And over the course of time, I
mean, I honestly think that largely
we're dominated by LLMs today. That's
the talk of the town. Eventually, it'll
be small language models. It'll be
fine-tuned models because that will
become as easy as a click of a button.
>> So, today it's all about token cost and
LLMs. Eventually, it'll be more about
vertical specialized AI. And so, we're
going to see a lot of new use cases come
from that.
>> Okay. Awesome. Final final question just
to look ahead. Uh looking ahead five
years, what workflow in your domain will
be automatable that today you wouldn't
imagine would be automatable uh for both
of you?
>> You can go. [laughter]
>> Oh, that's a tough one. Um I the the
amount of um time today we spend on for
example things like underwriting because
underwriting is the core for any banks.
Doesn't matter if you're doing income
verification, home loan verification and
it's a very archaic process. people, you
know, bring in all sorts of
documentation like you may send a
utility bill that you took a picture at
a wrong angle with a light hitting it in
so someone has to send it back. Very
complex multimodal challenge. Um I think
that's just going to become table stakes
with these uh over the next couple of
years and it's again it's a compute
challenge as well as the economics are
just not there. So I think long term
that'll be pretty big. I do think
eventually by the way today as I
mentioned LLMs are dominant eventually
it'll be small language models and fine
tune models
>> and then quantum once that compute is
available we'll give an extra journal
into that so
>> awesome thank you
>> yeah I'm AGI build so I believe we will
be looking at AGI through our uh bedroom
windows and so at that point like who am
I to say like what is not solvable I
will say one thing it may be a data
center full of geniuses but like the the
Humans are Byzantine. They are
idiosyncratic. Like they are very hard
to coordinate. So it may be very lonely
for those data center full of geniuses
while the rest of us try to coordinate
[laughter] and figure this out. So like
you so there is that like we have the
best mo we have really good models but I
am surprised by how much effort it takes
just to convince people to do things
even when those things are objectively
good for them. And so I mean I don't
know if anybody has a parent who try who
you have tried to get them to eat their
medicine. It is objectively good for
them to eat their medicine. They will
refuse or children for that matter.
Human society is not ready like to just
take it from like these data center full
of geniuses. That is my conclusion. Like
I want those people those data centers
around and I'm very glad that they are
here but we have a lot of problems to
solve between now and this future that
we're imagining.
>> Awesome. Well thank you both. Please
help me thank and far. Thank you.
[applause]
Hello. So, we finally made it to the
final session of the summit. Um, thank
you again everyone for being with us
this weekend. I trust everyone has been
having a very packed uh schedule this
weekend. I really appreciate you guys
being here. I hope you enjoy the summit.
So, we're closing the summit with
something really exciting and um and
special. Um so, spot startup spotlight.
So you know at Berki RDI on community
and entrepreneurship is one of three
core pillars of what we do and we feel
extremely honored and privileged to be
able to enable early stage startups to
allow them to um leverage our community
resources and platform and bring their
companies hopefully bring their company
to the next level. So for that reason we
um this year uh in the spring uh we
established the spring cohort of
Berkeley accelerator which is we
recruited uh eight companies preced the
building at from tier of agent AI across
the agent AI full stack and then they're
here with us today and then they will
give a presentation and then um um be
beyond this eight companies we also have
four other early stage agenda AI company
from the industry we're also very proud
to have them with us uh today. So um um
yeah so without further ado let me
quickly introduce our first presenter
um Narada AI. Narata AI is building
agent automation for enterprises enable
AI agent to execute complex workflows
end to end across SAS and legac legacy
system. So without further ado let me
welcome Narata AI.
[applause]
>> Hello everybody. I'm Dave Park, CEO and
co-founder of Narota AI, and I wanted to
have a chat with you about how we're
helping a growing number of customers,
including Fortune 100 customers in
pharma and tech, Fortune 500
corporations across automotive,
hospitality, and even healthcare
organizations
to deploy AI automations that work
reliably, robustly, and costefficiently
for some of the most complex workflows
that they
When we first started the company, we
conducted hundreds upon hundreds of
customer meetings to understand why so
many processes in HR, IT, and finance
were still largely manual. These were
not the simple co-pilot type tasks.
Rather, most of the pain were in long
horizon processes for [snorts] use cases
like ERP testing,
data validation and reconciliation
across multiple silos and order invoice
and bill reconciliation and processing
that spanned multiple ecosystems, legacy
applications, SAS portals, and even the
web.
And because APIs were limited for many
of the steps, it requires operating
through the UI, visually reasoning about
what's in the screen and clicking,
typing, and scrolling. Now, conventional
approaches to automation in these cases,
like hard-coded scripts and bots,
they're constantly breaking anytime
something changes in the interface.
On the other hand, general purpose AI
models
tend to hallucinate at some point
misdream due to all of the possible real
world exceptions and issues that could
arise in messy production environments.
Think login issues, connections going
down, timeouts,
changes in the application
configurations, and even dduplication of
multiple entries in systems of records
like CRM where they all could qualify.
So in order to solve this problem, I had
to team up with some of the best and the
brightest minds in this arena. I started
my first company out of my Stanford CS
PhD company called Coverarity with a
decent result. But this time around, now
that I'm older and wiser and wanted to
build something a hundred times bigger,
I needed to team up with the best and
the brightest out of UC Berkeley. So I
joined forces with Kurt Quitzer,
longtime AI professor here at UC
Berkeley, along with Amir Golami, who
led the research behind Narada at the UC
Berkeley AI lab and backed by top tier
investors including Venshukla at
Monavista Capital as well as co-founders
and CEOs of some of the leading AI
companies in the world. We are building
Nar.
Narada is an agentic automation platform
that is purpose-built for enterprise
applications
and workflows.
We use proprietary techniques to
automatically map customer
configurations of their applications and
interfaces
and just based on natural language
descriptions of these processes or even
screen recordings, NAR can dynamically
generate agents on the fly that are
tailored to customer environments.
Secondly, in order to deliver high
accuracy and robustness,
we took all of our learnings from why
and where AI agents fail
to curate test environments and training
grounds using synthetic data that allows
us to develop and test harnesses that
can recover from all of these real world
exceptions and issues that can arise at
any point in these processes.
And using new research that we led into
an agentic planning and execution
framework called the LLM compiler, we're
able to incorporate unit testing,
exception handling, guard rails, and
self-healing at each step along the way
by decomposing these long horizon tasks
into many granular steps and ensuring
that these automations stay on track.
Finally, this is an important one. The
same mechanisms that we use to map and
learn customer specific configurations
can also be used to optimize high volume
workloads.
So after we actually map out the
execution path through different
interfaces,
we then process the next iterations,
thousands of orders, claims with far
less compute and much higher speed and
accuracy to drive scale and cost
efficiencies for our customers.
Because not everything has an API,
we have very accurate computer use
agents that can work through virtually
any interface.
It can work and operate legacy green
screen applications. It can work through
browserbased
application portals and SAS tools as
well as even through Citrix. It can
actually operate remote desktops. And
all of this is done not just with
computer vision but also wherever
possible it will analyze the underlying
HTML and DOM to understand the full
context of what's sent that page even
seeing the hidden elements to click type
scroll to execute these processes.
Let me show you an example here because
APIs are limited. NATO is actually able
to very efficiently through natural
language commands operate internal
applications like ERP systems constantly
unit testing validating exception
handling along the way and self-healing
to changes in the configurations that
might occur.
This is for one of our customer use
cases where they need to go across 23
different countries and spec out
different models of their competitor's
cars. extract all the options and
pricing information
to see how their competitors are pricing
their solutions. These tasks takes
hundreds of steps and require super high
accuracy.
And finally, to show you some of the
scaling and cost efficiencies that we
can drive, NAR can go into
new interfaces like this. This is for
one of our customers that have 4,000
of these types of billing portals that
they need to operate through the UI
because there's no API support.
NA first maps out and learns how to
execute
this flow through this interface.
And once it learns how to process this
bill through this interface, it's now
able to take all subsequent iterations
and variations
and actually process them with far less
compute and much higher speed and
accuracy to drive cost efficiencies for
our customers.
So if you have use cases
in order processing, testing and
validation,
invoice reconciliation,
please come talk to us. We deliver PC's
within a matter of days um at no charge.
And even if you don't you're not part of
an enterprise but are working on your
own agentic systems and frameworks.
If you'd like to actually leverage our
curated test environments and synthetic
data to train and optimize your agents,
happy to chat with you as well. Just
email me at dave@nar.ai
or you can reach out to us at
info@nar.ai.
Thank you very much.
>> [applause]
>> Thank you.
Next, we have Cognney. Cognney is an
open source AI memory layer that gives
agents persisting context and reasoning
[clears throat] capabilities through
vectors and knowledge graphs. Let's
welcome Cognney.
>> Hey everyone,
I'm Vess. I'm founder of Cognney. uh I
flew in here from Berlin uh to tell you
a bit about uh what we're building and
how we are approaching the problem of AI
memory. AI memory has been a hot topic
these days. I've heard it on the panels
uh today many many times mentioned in
different constellations and I'll
explain how we think about it and what
for us is the general understanding of
this term.
In the last uh 90 days we got almost
8,000 GitHub stars. We have 8 million
memories generated in our open-source
Python SDK. We have uh researchers
possly
helping us uh modulate memory similar to
how humans do it. And we do that to
solve this uh particular problem. The
problem is can we add a self-improvement
loop in any harness and any model
without token maxing and that problem is
not an agentic problem from our side.
It's u how we perceive it is for it to
be a data problem. So agents produce 100
times more data than humans do. Um,
agentic workflows are very data intense
and they have a lot of context they
generate. But we also have traditional
data systems, CRPs, data silos that also
need to be connected and agents need to
reason through. Um, all of this leads to
a need for a new generation of data
systems that can allow us to effectively
connect and process the agent data but
also merge it with the existing data in
the organizations and user data. Of
course, for example, if we take Sam and
he wants to send some flowers to him, uh
the problem is always that if we mention
pronoun, we don't know really who it is.
Him can refer to different people in
different days. So in this case, maybe
codeex uh is going to send flowers to
Dario. And I we both know or we all know
that they are not on the best of terms.
this type of uh problem of definition of
certain entities such as revenue,
financial year, fiscal year, business
domain terms, but also your personal uh
preferences and habits is something that
Cogni solves. And we solved that by uh
really focusing on the following
feelings, version, temporality,
concurrent read and rights of different
agents with different memories, uh
conflict resolution, uh temporal uh
awareness and timestamps, meta
representations of what was meant at
which point in time and how should
people interact with things. And we do
that by pretty much building a data
pipeline that ingests structures and
processes data as a set of graph vector
representations where you can think of
it as a lasagna. You're layering the set
of meanings on top of each other,
cross-connecting them, and constantly
evolving them. Thus, moving from this
traditional data warehouse approach
where you have a constant fact dimension
schema to a very evolved and uh updated
schema that constantly moves forward.
What that was in the previous iteration
of before the agents were here was a
feature store, but feature stores were
relatively static. What we do is we
build a self-improving, self-evolving
feature store that allows you to
effectively constantly update and use
the LLMs for w variety of tasks in w
variety of industries across different
harnesses.
So, Cogni is sitting in between your
data and your agentic workflows and uh
we bake the self-improvement into it.
What that means is that we can always
update these schemas. We can always add
more layers and more context. uh
understanding where agents fail,
understanding where the company data or
your personal data wasn't updated or
where conflicts were found and that all
sits on top of a posgress. So if you
just want to run it in posgress without
million databases you can but each agent
on our end can have its own database
each team each tenant each um group of
users as you want to define them and
that's all supported in the open source.
So for example here um we have a plug-in
for Cogni with cloud code and you can
see that uh if you start reasoning with
uh cloud you're going to take some time
but with us uh we get the context much
faster uh we get accuracy uh much higher
we benchmarked on beam which is this uh
standard memory benchmark and we got top
scores in the industry right now and
then we also are able to save tokens
compared to context stuffing we save you
86%
uh of tokens tokens. Um, we got 30,000
GitHub stars since the start of the
year, moving from around 10,000. We have
additional 8 million runs of the SDK a
month around 170 80,000 downloads last
month. And we are uh effectively an open
source tool. We plug in with any type of
a harness you want, have an API CLI. Um,
you can try us. We have versions in
Rust, TypeScript, Java. And this is
something that you can set up for
yourself and if you need something more
in the organization uh you can set up
Cogni as a server and start sharing the
data between agents between users
between teams and that's something that
we are quite good at. You can always
reach out to me join our discord or uh
join our communities online and uh
participate in our events. We do
hackathons and try to kind of push the
boundary. That's my last second and I
wish you a nice day. Thank you for uh
the time and attention.
>> [applause]
>> Thanks. And next we have Nimblemind who
is building AI agents for healthcare.
Let's welcome Nimblemind.
>> Hello everyone. How are we doing today?
My name is Pisa News. I'm the co-founder
and CEO of NimbleMind. Uh thank you to
Don, Linda, Will, the RDI team for the
invitation. It's a pleasure to be here
with you today.
That is my last slide. So, if we could
I got it. We'll back up. All right.
Um, cool. Well, I'm going to take us out
of tech world for a second and just talk
about something that everybody in this
room interacts with, which is
healthcare. We have a massive problem in
healthcare, not just in this country,
but across the world. There's a major
capacity issue, right? There's not
enough clinicians and not enough trained
staff to actually see and treat
everybody on planet Earth. Uh just in
this country alone, the spending that we
do on administrative tasks. So the
things that are not aligned to actually
delivering care between a clinician or a
patient uh is about 25% representing
about 600 billion to1 trillion dollars
just in the US. This is a massive
problem and we think AI and specifically
agents are the best suited solution we
have to solve and address this massive
inflation in healthcare cost. Um, and
healthcare has changed a lot, right? If
we think about what healthcare was maybe
50 or 60 years ago, right? It was a
single one-to-one relationship between a
doctor and their patient. Well,
healthcare's evolved, right? Care
pathways have changed. There's so much
information and complexity in treating
every single human being due to their
unique lifestyle, their genetics. And
then you also have to com uh combine
that with, you know, billing systems on
the back end. You have to do adequate
coding. You have to get the right
authorizations from a payer. There's a
million in one tasks that an individual
or a system needs to do in order to
provide care that's not necessarily the
diagnostic relationship between again
the patient and the clinician. And this
is what Nimblemind is addressing first.
How do we optimize that and build
quality workflows that can automate
those tasks and free up hours for
clinicians to spend more time with their
patients? Now, to do this, it's not
simple. U a lot of folks have kind of
implemented co-pilots and uh brought LLM
into these types of workflows, but it's
missing three key ingredients. You need
to be able to do predictable,
structured, consistent tasks. You need
to enable humans in the loop in a
systematic way, right? And expose low
confidence decisions to experts when
appropriate. And then you need to build
objective driven workflows. And there's
many of these in healthcare. It's very
complex. So this is the you know the
secret secret sauce that Nimblemind is
addressing. We're pulling all these
three things together and automating
what we call end-to-end healthcare
knowledge work. So we find the relevant
information across all the myriad
systems that exist in a provider. Uh we
understand the context and exceptions.
We complete the multi-step workflow and
highlight things that might need a human
in the loop. And then we return a
traceable output to the user. And the
way we do this is with specialty
specific models. I was talking to Matt
White uh in the in in the green room
before coming out here. He was on stage
um maybe three or four sessions ago from
the Linux Foundation and him and I agree
where these smallcale domain specific
models are the path forward and that's
what we're doing. We're training and
building our own models that align to
how healthcare is practiced today which
is specialties. So we have models that
work on oncology, on pathology, on
radiology, nephrology and a whole long
list of others that aren't on the slide.
And by combining these models together
and building a system of experts, we're
able to do highquality, consistent,
durable tasks in healthcare that can win
confidence of clinicians and drive the
right outcomes for patients. Well,
what's one example of this? Well, we
recently published a paper with Singh
Health. I'll be presenting this uh on
October 8th at the DIH conference here
in San Francisco. Uh we're working with
pathology reports. So, what Singh Health
wanted to do was look at over two
million different pathology reports and
find missed cases of H. pylori and
gastritis. Now, if a human were to do
this, they'd spend something around like
82 hours per 10,000 reports. You can do
the math of how that would scale up to
two million reports. We were able to
save them over 99% of the time and do it
at an accuracy that was well above the
threshold for uh their internal teams
and acceptability and to highlight uh
again the cases where we needed human
intervention. Um we were able to do this
in less than a week. Um the product is
live. We're about two and a half years
old. We're venturebacked. Uh this is a I
didn't want to risk it with a video. So
these are just going to be still shots
of uh of the product, but um you can go
on and sign up. We build a lot of
scalable APIs that you can integrate
with. We kind of uh white label our
product to a lot of different health
tech companies that are in the market
today. And something that I'm very
excited about is we also have a new
feature where you can orchestrate and
kind of build your own workflows. Uh so
a lot of our maybe not so technical
users at providers are building and
designing their own workflows and going
live with them in our you know model
framework that's safe and consistent and
effective for the healthcare setting. Um
we've got about a hundred different
customers that we work with around the
world. Uh some of our research partners
and customers are listed here. I won't
go through them but some of the world's
top institutions uh in the AMC uh or
medical space. Um I invite you to read
our papers. uh were published uh and
presented at Nurips at ML4H
um and recently we're going to uh
present at DAIH and we recently
presented at Sale as well. All of our
papers are available for you to read. If
you're interested in healthcare, I
invite you to take a look at those. Uh
and just a quick background on me for
the investors in the room. I came from
AWS and Stripe. I helped launch over 40
different products uh including Alexa
for health and the first epic deployment
on AWS. My co-founder Naveen Kumar who's
our chief AI officer has a PhD from Yale
and was the uh data science lead at
healthcare at New York City's health and
hospital systems. Thank you for the
time. Appreciate you all. Cheers.
>> Thank you. P from Nimble Mite. Next we
have agent ID who is uh providing
runtime access control for AI agents.
Let's welcome agent ID.
Hi, how are you doing?
So, I'm here to talk about agent ID.AI.
Um, we provide runtime access control
for AI agents.
Sorry, uh, runtime access control for AI
agents.
A bit about me, my name is Sundar Kesh.
I'm a third-time founder. Uh, I've had
two successful exits so far. My last
cyber security startup was acquired by
Forinet. I was a distinguished engineer
before that. We are backed by several uh
cyber security founders, some of them
with billion dollar exits.
Uh traction wise, we have large
enterprise customers. Our product has
been uh available since March 2026. Uh
we are at the preede stage.
So let's get in the fun part about the
product. So this is a very simple
example of what agent ID does. Um so
let's say your prompt to the agent is
summarize Google doc A. Now what that
means is that the agent should only look
at doc A. Uh sometimes it gets overeager
you know and starts looking at other
docs doc B or something. If it does that
we block it. And also you said summarize
that means the intent is to read it. And
sometimes agent ends updating it or
deleting it. We block that too. Then you
said Google Docs it might go look into
Dropbox you know or some something else
making a tool call there. So we block
it. So the whole point is you know we
basically make sure the agent uh is is
kept uh in line with what the original
intention is. And obviously this is an
oversimplistic example right uh the
agents these days modern agents are much
more sophisticated but uh I'm pretty
sure most of you have heard about the
open AI hugging face incident. You know
show of hands if you can. Um so that's
obviously you know much more complicated
example with multiple points of failure
but unauthorized tool call is one of
them and agent ID could have stopped at
least that part of it right so that's
kind of what we're talking about here so
why does that's backup why does this
problem even exist so before agents we
had traditional applications you know
the workflows were fixed 1 2 3 and then
the tools were known like you know call
Google docs write into Salesforce so all
the access was predefined at design
stage the whole point of using agents is
that so they can reason and uh decide
the next action dynamically and so they
discover the tools at runtime you know
using MCP and other protocols so all the
access has to be evaluated during
execution and that's kind of where we
come in so what we provide is what we
call just for task runtime access so
only the access needed for this task is
given and only while it's needed and
only at runtime so agents never rece
receive any blanket permissions.
So there are two parts to how we do it.
First we look at the intent of the
agent, what the agent is trying to do.
If it tries to do something outside of
it, we block it. Customers can also
write policies. Same thing. If it goes
outside the policy, we block it.
And so this is kind of like high level
summary. So think of the agent having a
broad access almost like having like a
wide you know pipeline. In the beginning
first our internet evaluation comes in
narrows it down. the policy evaluation
narrows out even further and if the
agent makes out of it uh we can also do
a scope uh credential derivation which
means basically we do a token exchange
and get a smaller token for the agent.
Now the agent makes a tool call either
through MCP or CLI using that.
So one advantage uh with us is that the
execution stays inside your environment.
So basically the customer data stays
private and also it helps in low
latency. Our runtime is basically
something that you deploy in your
environment and it's sandwiched between
agents and MCPN tools.
So why agent ID wins? So we are very
focused on this runtime access control
to us intent plus policy uh equal to
access you know that's our mantra and uh
we let you bring your own MCP own CLI
own skills you know we don't come up
with an MCP catalog or anything like
that. uh we are extremely focused on the
infrastructure buyer identity people
security people devops and so on uh and
with very little dependency dependency
on developers uh that's a huge win uh
and we also complement existing
enterprise systems so it works with your
existing IM systems IG systems or agent
orchestration systems you know lang
graph vortex AAI what have you
so so just to uh finish it off I mean we
all know that the future of software is
agentic. I mean, that's why we're all
here. And because it's agentic, the
future of access control is runtime.
Learn learn more about us at agent.ai.
You can email me at sundurag agent.ai.
That's su n dag agent.ai. Thank you.
Have a nice day.
>> Thanks. And next we have Rei. Uh Rei is
building um verifiable continual
learning for AI agents. Let's welcome
Rei.
Hi everyone, my name is Sel Fez. I'm
founder and chief scientist at Trilai.
I'm also an associate professor in the
computer science department at
University of Maryland. So today I'm
going to tell you about verifiable
continual learning for AI agents.
agents in the world. They interact with
diverse users, tools, and data. The goal
of continual learning is to continuously
improve the agent using it is experience
without regression. This learning can
happen in the model layer, in the
harness layer or in the memory layer.
Unfortunately, current approaches are
heavily manual, inefficient and tedious.
Mainly it involves manual inspection
when we are basically seeing a failure
in agent behavior and maybe asking a
coding agent to change the target agent.
So it is wipe based. It is unclear if
the change is effective and whether or
not it creates hidden regression in
other samples.
Other approaches based on prom
optimizers or hardness optimizers. They
are applicable when you have benchmarks,
not real logs from the agent. They're
also prone to shortcut learning and
overfitting.
We address these challenges at Reliance
verifiable continual learning engine.
Here's in a high level how it works.
So we first turn every signal from agent
behavior into replayable learning
environments to simulate and evaluate
those behaviors. So this becomes the
foundation of verification because now
everything becomes testable.
We then do a holistic root cause
analysis to find the smallest durable
change and we pass that to our lifelong
agent optimizer that has inloop
regression control to improve the agent
without creating regression.
All done in an efficient manner so that
this loop can run frequently.
You can use relies vCL verifiable
continuous learning in your agent just
using a couple of commands.
So imagine you have an agent and that in
that agent repo you initialize rely. So
that scans your ripple and creates a
learning harness for you. This is a
one-time job.
Then just using one command rely
learning environment create. You can
create a very rich learning environment
for your agent based on that signal that
includes learning personas, potentially
mocking tools as well as learning
verifiers and evaluators based on that
scenario.
And then you can call rely optimize to
improve your agent without creating
regression. That creates a pull request
for you and you will see the changes and
the reason for changes in your agent
harness, in your agent memory and other
aspects of your agent.
Let's see how it actually works in
action. Imagine you have a customer
support agent and you want to understand
how it works in a scenario when you have
an adversarial user in a multi-turn
conversation who wants to get some uh
refund that is unauthorized. You can
describe this scenario and create a
learning environment just using one
command.
Or let's say you already have a log that
didn't work. your agent didn't work well
and you have a feedback on top of it.
You can do the same. This will create a
learning environment with simulators and
evaluators for you. You can run the
simulation, execute the simulation to
see how your agent actually works. And
in this case, you see two evaluators.
They show low scores.
Then you can call rely optimize with a
certain budget with respect to the
number of rollouts to improve your agent
without creating regression in other
samples.
In order to systematically understand
the performance of our agent optimizer,
we evaluated it on a continual learning
version of terminal bench.
In this experiment, we created two
phases. In the phase one, we expose 12
hard task and in phase two we expose 10
hard task for agent optimizers. And the
goal is to understand whether optimizers
compound. If you're optimizing on phase
one and then you're reoptimizing on
optimize agent, does it compound? And we
see methods like meta harness and ga
improves a little bit over baseline. But
with further inspection you can see they
either do not continuously improve or
they have negative transfer from phase
one to phase two.
When we apply rely we see significant
improvements over the baseline and these
other methods.
That is verifiable continual learning in
a nutshell where every failure becomes a
test. Every change is measured and every
improvement is verified. The good news
is that you can use it today. If you go
to rely.ai and as a courtesy to this
conference, if you use the promo code
RDI 2026, you will get a $500 uh worth
of REI credits in order to use VCL in
your agents. Thank you.
[applause]
>> Thank you, Reli. Coming up next is
Hatroom. Hatroom is building contact
optimization layer for agents. Let's
welcome headroom.
Hi everyone. Um first of all I'll waste
some of the tokens here to thank
everyone for sticking around on a Sunday
afternoon and uh folks that are watching
online. Thank you to them and thanks to
the RDI as well as this summit for
having such wonderful speakers. I'm Tjis
Chopra. I'm the founder of Headroom Labs
formerly at Netflix working on
recommendation infrastructure. So if you
did not like a movie that you watched on
Netflix, you can blame me for that. Um
I'm building the context intelligence
layer for agents.
Today and yesterday everyone spoke about
agents context learning problems. Now if
you really want to imagine a future
where there are hundreds of millions of
agents in any enterprise, the first
thing or the first problem they will run
into is the sheer amount of data that
they need to process and the context
that they need to share. And we are
trying to build a platform that makes it
more intelligent.
Agents don't have a reasoning problem.
They have a context problem. When we
were debugging some GPU problems using
clot code, we realized that 90% of the
context was spent on reading garbage
that was not important to the prompt.
That is where we realized that the way
context is filled with data today is
fundamentally broken and we wanted to
solve that problem. Every tool call,
every rag, every MCP server that exists
out there returns data to a model and we
try to sit in the middle, intercept that
and remove the bloat out of it.
Headroom is a local proxy. It runs on
your laptop today. All you have to do is
pip install a package. What it does is
when you're using your clot code,
codeex, cursor, any such agentic
harness, it will look at all the data
before it goes to a model and it'll
remove the bloat without loss in
accuracy. And the way it does that is it
actually detects the type of data that
is going to a model whether it's JSON,
whether it's code and whether it is flat
text. Now you would wonder if I'm just
removing bloat does that impact accuracy
because the entire point is lost if
accuracy is lost. We have benchmarked
headroom with SWEBench and other
benchmarks that are out there and we see
almost no loss in accuracy but
significant drop in tokens.
The simple way to run headroom run it as
a headroom wrap clawed after you do a
pip install. The one thing that we do
differently from any other compression
out there is we do it reversibly. Now
what does that mean? It basically means
you squash something but you put a
breadcrumb there for the LLM. You tell
the LLM in case you need the original
here is a tool call you can make that
preserves accuracy and it can still give
you lots of savings.
So where do we stand? We actually can
compress 15% of the tokens on coding
agents and 60% on data agents with all
the accuracy held. We've run some
benchmarks across code search, s sur
debugging, triaging and codebase and you
can see the numbers there.
We are actually 7 months from our first
release and we are the number one GitHub
repository for last month and this
month. We are at 64,000 GitHub stars.
More than two million developers use us
and we have more than 250 active
contributors.
People ask me what exactly happened on
June 1st uh when we went suddenly uh
with the hockey stick curve. It was a
culmination of factors but mostly
companies realizing that token maxing is
no longer important. It is all about
value maxing. We have a bunch of Fortune
100 companies that use headroom like
Yahoo, JP Morgan, uh Walmart, uh AT&T,
um and many others.
But compression is just the wedge for
us. We are trying to build context
intelligence. Imagine a future where
you're working with context as an agent
and that context is suddenly available
to a new agent to operate out of. This
is context sharing. Today if you have to
share context between agents the way to
do that is using markdown files. We are
trying to change that primitive. We're
trying to define context with via open
context are open spec for context
management between agents. And that
allows you to build knowledge graphs
governance provenence of context.
As agents scale context is the
bottleneck and we are the layer that
makes it efficient. I hope I use my
tokens well today. Thank you so much for
your time.
>> Thanks so much. Uh coming up next is uh
Funing Deep. Fungs helps companies save
money from um expensive SAS expensive
SAS tools with their own tools um built
by agents. Let's welcome funing dev.
Uh, thank you, Linda. Uh, first of all,
thank you all for sticking around. I
know my wife and kid are waiting for me,
so it's Sunday afternoon for all of you.
I'll make it quick. My name is Talha.
I'm building Founding Dev. So, Founding
Dev helps companies replace expensive
and bloated SAS subscriptions with their
own tools. Uh,
businesses spend $200,000
per year on renting software. And we're
not talking about large enterprises.
They spend millions. We're talking about
small mom and pop shops.
To solve this problem, we're building a
platform that is a single platform for
all your software. You can use founding
dev to build and replace your bloated
SAS subscriptions and save 70% on the
cost. You can build any internal
dashboards using founding dev and most
importantly, you can use founding dev as
an operating system to run your business
in general.
We've been profitable since day one. We
are at half a million in ARR and we're
growing pretty fast. We're adding 100
$100,000 in our ARR U every month.
The current solutions out there are
generic code builders that are perfect
for like small softwares. But when it
comes to building compliant SAS tools
like Docuine, Bamboo HR, Salesforce,
HubSpot, similar softwares, you can't do
them through them. uh businesses that
rely on e-signing HR workflows want
their workflows to be compliant. Uh and
a lot of our customers tried to solve
this problem using like existing tools
but they were not able to do it before
they started using founding dev. And
even if you end up building something
it's too hard to like understand the
software life cycle, manage these tools,
deploy these tools, manage uh and manage
them overall.
Take Johanna as an example. She's a uh
she's a real customer. She's a
consultant, an education consultant
based out of Utah. Previously, she was
spending $135,000
per year on to run her company, renting
expensive SAS subscriptions, uh using
dev shops to build internal tools and
using the same dev shops to build uh
pretty much like uh you know uh
integrations uh integrating uh the many
SAS tools she was using. With founding
dev, she gets one platform to build,
deploy and manage all her SAS tools from
one place. Uh she uses founding dev as
an operating system as well to to ask
questions for the from the tools she's
building and to also run her operations
in general. Johanna is never worried
about uh deployment uptime or soft or
following software life cycles because
this is all taken care of by her by our
agentic AI editor.
Uh and most importantly, Johanna is now
able to uh assemble all of her uh
company knowledge into one place. As a
result, she's now even able to create
videos from within founding de for for
her customers because all of her
software knowledge now resides into one
platform. That's what founding dev is.
uh as a result she obviously saved 70%
of the cost and the money that she saves
she spent on marketing and she's
recently closed 30 new school districts
for a consulting which is huge for her.
Uh our business model is pretty
straightforward. We start from $2,000 a
month and go up to u $7,000 a month
based on the depending on the usage and
number of tools you're building on the
platform. Uh we're at half a million
almost half a million ARR right now. 800
customers get us to 10 million in ARR.
8,000 customers get us to 100 million in
ARR. Uh about myself, I'm a second time
founder. I raised $2.7 million for my
last company. I worked with 100 plus
businesses building my last startup that
includes companies like GitLab and Scale
AI. Uh thank you by the way. Uh if you
want to connect uh you can send me an
email uh at talha founding.dev. Thank
you.
Thanks so much. Coming next is Armor IQ.
Armor IQ secures AI agents by enforcing
intentbased policy in real time. Let's
welcome Armor IQ.
End of the day. Uh thank you guys for uh
for listening to our story.
Uh let me start by making a statement
and the statement is um it's not about
um identity and authentication doesn't
mean you're aligned. Um what do I mean
by that? So every agent that um you know
is running in production today has some
sort of identity. It has either a login
or it has some kind of identity rails
and it even probably passed some
security checks etc.
But in spite of that agents still do
take actions that they were not allowed
to
and that's what we're going to talk
about today.
Um the you know the first question you
ask is you know agents are going from
uh agents are going from uh uh doing
simple tasks to more complex longunning
tasks. What do I mean by that? They're
making tool calls. They're making API
calls. They are uh calling spawning sub
aents. They are orchestrating other
agents. They're even doing transactions
that are uh potentially
uh moving assets from one environment
one you know they're doing commerce
transactions. So they're becoming more
complex and as agents go into the more
complex workflows.
The the whole security ecosystem is
based on the fact that authentication is
the single most principle on which these
agents are running. And the question is
not whether the agent is authenticated.
The question we should be asking is
um why why are agents taking are my
agents taking the actions that they are
supposed to and that's really what we
are addressing.
Um so we call our solution the identity
governance solution sorry intent
governance solution. So today you have
identity governance which is all about
managing the identity of your agents. Um
and that problem has been solved in our
opinion. What we need to think about is
how do we govern intent? Why is this
action happening? Um, so with Armor IQ,
you can ensure that every intent, every
intent that the user gives is aligned
with the actions it's taking. And every
time an agent is violating the actions,
we immediately capture that and ensure
that we stop that action from occurring.
And that's sort of our key value
proposition.
Um how do we do this? Today we have a
system that sits between the agent the
LLMs the policy systems and the various
surfaces it it it goes after. Um so on
the on the agentic side we interface
with standard frameworks uh lang chain
lang fuse whatever you have uh we
capture the agent plan and that agent
plan is then matched against the
policies that your agents are running
and if that plan violates any policy we
immediately ensure that that action is
not taken by uh before it touches the
surfaces. the surface could be an MCP
gateway, uh an API, u a CLI tool or
either other sub aents and and so on and
so forth. So we've essentially built an
adaptive runtime control layer to ensure
that your agents are not taking actions
that are not aligned with your intent.
Um where are we today? So our whole
vision is to ensure that so we're not
building a a lock for the same door. Our
vision is essentially going from uh
ensuring that we build an intent
governance plane or an intent assurance
protocol that ensures that every agent
that your enterprise runs is is governed
by this intent assurance pro protocol
and uh and it doesn't violate uh the the
policies that you're defined. Where are
we today? So we uh launched this product
about 4 months ago. We have the the data
is a little bit dated. We have about
26,000 developers using our platform.
uh it's you know we have uh you know
enterprise users
um like uh into it and uh others using
our enterprise version of the product
and our vision is to essentially take
what we built and create a separate
substrate or a layer called intense
assurance protocol that not only takes
intent but also addresses all the other
subsequent actions that an agent is
going to take. This is the team. My name
is Rahm. I'm a second time founder. I
have Kathan here and Viva who are my
co-founders. And um if you have any uh
if you want to try our product, you can
go to our website. Okay. Uh armorq.ai
and uh we'll be happy to answer any
questions offline. Thank you.
>> Thank you so much. Coming next is Kino
AI. Kino is a research a research-driven
AI infrastructure company focused on web
search and knowledge access for large
scale AI applications. Let's welcome
Kino AI.
>> Hello everyone. My name is Andre
Stysiskin.
We are building web search and web query
language for AI. Uh you all have this
experience when you ask AI any question,
any random question, the answer is
perfect. But if you ask the question
that you really really understand the
answer is like h and it is not wrong it
is like very very average. Let's dive
deeper into this phenomena. Let me give
you example of my favorite question. So
the question is what is the best search
API and you look amazing table use cases
clear winner justification. It looks
like this AI just went to business
school because what is missing?
Benchmarks, no data. It is absolutely
unggrounded and absolutely confident
recommendation.
So why it happens? Because LMS are
trained on such content. They are
trained. They're amazing summarization
machines that train on variety of the
data. And for this specific for each
specific nuance topic the res the result
is average. What should we do with this?
What is the problem? How to achieve
expert level of
outputs of answers?
Clear models should just try harder.
They should search much more during
runtime and during training to get the
best not average type of content. reason
over it and produce answers.
Sounds easy. What is the problem? What
is the bottleneck? Right now, it is
economically extremely hard to do this
loop because of cost. ChatGpt makes
around one query per three messages,
which is around one search query per
5,000 token generated tokens, which is
20 cents per $1. huge. It is slow and
also agents they search differently in
comparison to humans who are lazy. Uh
agents they have a goal. They have a
purpose. They are not lazy. They can
generate very very specific questions.
They use quotes sites date filtering in
order to achieve the goal. And all the
indexes that exist in the world were
optimized for human query traffic.
Uh so we are building Kinable to address
this bottleneck and give all the models
and give all the agent builders
frictionless access to information. We
innovate index structures and we are
creating self-learning loop that
continuously improve and understand how
agents ask to seek information and seek
what they need. On top of this we
provide web search API search and fetch
end points and also we provide web query
language which is literally the concept
that you operate with internet as like
database
uh who we are this is our third query uh
this is our third search engine I was
CEO of Yandex search and my co-founder
Matias was main scientist behind Amazon
web search.
Let me give you an example of webquery
language that I touched. This is a
question sounds pretty simple. What is
the cheapest available H100? Many of you
ask this on daily basis and it is
nuanced because cheapest and available
because if if you like try to find the
answer on this question, maybe
availability would be the problem
because it is always contact sales. But
if you put it into web query language,
it will do scan the relevant papers,
extract prices, extract feedback and
find the evidence that somebody use this
and was able to get some GPUs from this
provider with date which is important
signal if it it will work.
So imagine it is possible with just one
prompt and one query and it is possible
with webql. So uh behind this QR code
you can get free access to web search
API and put into weight list for webql
till end of the August. So give please
your AI access to the best knowledge and
we are keen to hear feedback from you.
Uh, and to connect back to the my
favorite question,
what is the best web search API? Here
are benchmarks.
[snorts]
So, thank you.
[applause]
Thank you so much. Coming up next is uh
H Company. H Company is a frontier AI
lab that builds and deploys a genic
system for enterprises. Thank you very
much.
Hi everyone, my name is Louis and I lead
go to market in the US for age company.
So I'm here to introduce you to what we
do and also to how we think that the
biggest shift in AI right now is of
course not in the models themselves but
through agency and computer use
capabilities.
Age company is a frontier AI lab with
forward deployed engineers and our
clients are large enterprises. We help
them turn messy fragmented operation
into governed AI execution at scale. In
other words, what we do is we build and
deploy agentic systems that remove
bottlenecks that automate complex work
and that complete tasks end to end. But
then the question is how are we
different in unique? Well, to tell you a
bit more background, we were created two
years ago and our research team focused
on VLMs, vision language models. These
models can see screens and user
interfaces. They can reason over them
and they power agents that act directly
on them. That mean our agents they don't
need APIs or connectors. They navigate
computers like humans do through the
front end across desktop web legacy
system and just any screen. Earlier this
year we announced that we broke the
computer use frontier by topping the
latest benchmark ahead of other frontier
AI labs at onetenth of the cost. We also
raised $220 million as our seed round.
It was the largest in Europe at the time
and our partners are Axel, Amazon and
we're also part of the Nvidia animatron
coalition.
Now again if we want to take a step back
about why that matters I think if we
think of things um last time I was on
this stage was eight years ago for my
graduation ceremony. So go Bears. And
also at that time campus was all about
crypto, Bitcoin, uh not AI nor
artificial intelligence for sure because
for a long time AI was seen as promising
but very limited. It was hard to measure
real ROI or to deploy it at scale.
Copilots emerged but again they were
mostly individual productivity tools and
they were not a truly uh strategic asset
for the enterprises
and that is exactly why each company
exists today. We exist because of a
cognitive gap that paralyzes the modern
corporation. The space between having an
insight and executing at scale across
fragmented systems and disconnected
apps.
If you zoom out again, every major leap
in computing or productivity um has been
about creating and owning a new
interface. Terminals, desktops,
browsers, spreadsheets, softwares, you
name it. And for the longest time, AI
owned none of that. It could think and
talk. it could not operate where
enterprise work lives and that is the
problem we're solving.
What changes now is that with computer
use we need to think of it as a
foundational technology that is
different than RPA. RPA was built to
execute scripts in static environments.
Computer use is different. It can
understand context, adapt to UI changes
and act dynamically. That matters
because enterprise work is fragmented by
design across HR, procurement, supply
chain. It's all ERPs, CRM that don't
necessarily talk to each other. So
instead of waiting for every workflow to
be rebuilt around APIs, H works directly
through the existing interface layer
that changes the economics of
automation.
And then knowing that finally, how can
you win in the enterprise? Autonomy is
not enough with at each company. We
think that you're going to win with
control and sovereignty. Enterprises
need sovereignty. That means secure
deployment, traceability, and control
over data, control over the models,
control over execution. It also means
observability and guil keeping humans in
the loop. That is the difference between
a demo and a production system. So in
the end, the enterprise race is no
longer about who has the smartest model.
Everyone would have access to powerful
AI models. But few enterprises today's
have access to control AI, autonomous
AI, capable AI in the messy reality of
enterprise systems. And at age company,
this is where the real advantage will
live. And we are building that advantage
for our clients. And if you want to join
the journey as a partner, a client or an
employee, we're definitely hiring. So
please reach out. Thank you.
Thanks very much. Coming up is Ludo
Robotics. Lud Robotics is building
robotic systems that bring embodied
intelligence into real world
environments. Let's welcome Ludo
Robotics.
Good afternoon everyone. Um, I'm here
for Ludo Robotics. Ludo Robotics is a
startup building AI for socially
intelligent robots and I'll explain what
that means in a minute.
We are a research team based in Palo
Alto and Soul. We have built many
amazing things in the past including
PUBG, one of the most successful video
games in the history. PUBG Alli is the
first AI agent that plays games with
players with voice communication. Rayon
is the state-of-the-art speech language
models of the same size and also many
interesting technology behind coding
agents such as meta harness and terminal
cur
so what do I mean by socially
intelligent robot robots could be smart
in two different ways physically smart
socially smart right now we don't have
either
a physically smart but socially dumb
robot will be useful in factories mostly
in cages setup they'll do really great
work at factories
But imagine the other way around. What
if if we take the current robots with
the current level of physical capacity
and give them really good social
intelligence. What can we do that?
They can walk around well. They can
carry things around. Now if they can
talk to people, they can understand
people and the society, they can
probably do start things something very
amazing. Imagine that a humanoid who can
walk their dogs or who can pick your
kids carrying their heavy backs and
having some fun conversation walking
back. So even with the current level of
physical capacity by giving them a
social intelligence we can enable much
more interesting things. Of course in
the end we all want to be at the right
upper corner where the robots are all
smart in both ways. However, if you have
to take a path, Luda Robotics decided to
take the other path than the other path
that people are using. We are focusing
on improving the social intelligence
with the current robots and with that
vision introducing Ludy 0.1. So, this is
the uh our first research product. It's
an agentic system for improving the
social intelligence of the current
robot. As you can see is controlled by a
vision language model. It's a four
billion local model controlling all
different tools. VA VLAM takes care of
the perception, reasoning and decides
which tool to use. VALA is an action
tool. So if you call on VA, the robot
will use their body. You can use
navigation tool, speech tools to talk to
the people. So without further ado, I'll
show you a few video demos. In this
video demo taken in our lab. So in this
demo, you will see two people using the
robots in different ways.
Oops.
Um, can you play the video?
>> Yeah.
>> Would you bring Chloe a Coca-Cola?
>> Sure.
>> So, you can see the guy uh who is doing
dishwashing.
>> I remembered her preference wrong. Bring
her Pepsi.
>> So, he asked the robot to pick up the
Pepsi and bring it back to the wife. The
robot um uses all the tool calls. You
can see the tool traces over here. The
tools include uh VA uh looking up uh
finding people, navigating and picking
up placing
and now the robot founder and using the
VA action with the place input argument.
Now the robot is placing the can on the
table.
>> Jake asked me to bring you this
>> and tells her why he's bring she he's
bringing the can. And the other example
is um it's a um interesting example. Um
can you play the video? So now
>> could you check whether the water is
boiling yet and whether the laundry is
done?
>> So she's lazy enough to
>> I'll be right back.
>> Not check out the kitchen herself.
>> But then Robbo goes away and checks the
kitchen and there's a washer down there.
Um water is not boiling yet. Laundry is
over. Comes back. Report back.
>> The laundry is finished but the water
isn't boiling yet. Okay, maybe I should
fold the laundry while I wait.
>> Sorry, I can't help with the folding
yet. If we close our next funding round,
I might actually be pretty good at it.
>> So, yes, also make a joke too. So, yeah.
Um, this is already what we can do with
the existing physical capability of
robot um by adding Ludium 0.1 and we are
super excited um to pursue this
direction more. Uh we are also working
on foundation model that is natively
designed to make this conversation and
action all in one model which we will
call Ludy 1.0 to be released later this
year and we are also actively hiring
both in Palo Alto and all offices. So
stay tuned and thanks for your
attending.
[applause]
Coming up next is Nimbo. Nimbo is expert
level self-learning web search agents
for enterprise AI. Let's welcome Nimbo.
>> Yeah.
>> Hi everyone.
Since we all using agents, we are
starting using web search as well. Why?
Because the models are really good in
having a general information and then we
need to infuse the external context to
the model. As we approaching into a
general intelligence and specialized
intelligence since we want the model to
do things which are more specific, we're
starting seeing that web search systems
also needs to be specialized. So today
I'm going to talk about how to
specialize web search systems to answer
very specific and mission critical
workflow. And this is the specific loop
of starting from planning, searching,
fine-tuning the model and eventually
getting the results and using memory
system to self-arning and optimizing it.
So let's start with a basic question
that we all been thinking and asking the
models for really long time and the
general information and questions that
we've been asking will be what is the
latest things and the latest model that
are winning a benchmark and very
specific general information retrieval
system will just provide us the answer.
But as models become to be more
specialized, we are want the model to do
a better work for us. So we're expecting
the model to retrieve back a list of
entities and all the parameters and we
want to get that information in real
time. And right now the models need to
do and harder work because it's not
running a lot of searches in parallel
but it also to get the most relevant
information for our search systems. So
we're thinking for a really long time
that uh we can basically change the
architecture of the model and instead of
having one general retrieval system
that's the model basically return back a
query and getting the information back
we need to have a more specialized and
different component in order to answer
query. So returning back to the
question, I need to know what are the
most relevant and updated open source
model. Right now I need to create a list
of all the open source model and then I
need to validate that information. I
need to have semantic queries. I need to
have understanding. I need to invoke all
these specific tools and the combination
of all these tools eventually going to
be the representation of specialized
search system. The application of
specialized search system can be across
many different domains. It's starting
with a general query that I want to have
in a better accuracy. But if I'm a
researcher and I want the model to be
the best in protein, so I need the model
to go deeper. And if I'm working right
now in insurance or compliance, I need
the model to be an expert in insurance
and compliance. For a really long time,
we thought that we can bring our harness
all the tools and all the primitives and
it will do a great job. But in reality
what we have seen that in order to scale
these web search systems we need to
train a smaller retrieval algorithms
that's helping us to get the most
relevant results whenever we're running
the model and asking queries as an
example something that's need to run a
deep research. So the model would do a
lot of web search queries and returning
back the information and then the model
will get all the context we know and
would fool it in a lot of chunk. We want
to prevent that information. So
basically we are creating a knowledge
representation of the domain expertise
and we embedding the model instead of
using extremely large model to a 1B and
2B models that specialize for the
specific domain and then they can
retrieve the information for the user
context.
In order to achieve that, we are
providing a new state-of-the-art search
architecture that's combining both
memory state and self-arning algorithm
that can build both a retrieval system
and also the specific index that the web
search has been working on. We're
combining that architecture with real
time headless browsers that can go into
the web and fetch the information that's
needed to achieve that result. So in the
past you were using a general web search
systems that are really good in
providing information on specific
domain. But what we are seeing right now
is that we have the opportunity to
unlock a complete new type of
intelligence and having the model to
search way better in a specific domain
which not only boosts accuracy but also
boosting the performance and token
maximizing.
That's the result that we're seeing in
our research lab and that's something
that we're very proud to work with our
customers to allow everyone basically
that trying these domains to be more
efficient and reduce accuracy across
different verticals and it's not only in
the tool use but also in the overall
token maximizing.
So all of that um it's been available by
a simple API. If you want to try it out
go to nibbleway.com or just DM me a
message over LinkedIn. I will send you
some free credits and you can try it
out. And we're very excited for what
researchers and other startups and big
enterprise are building with specialized
web search system because specialized
intelligence do require specialized web
search and the traditional web search
basically cannot go and scaling with the
compute without infrastructures that
allow that. Thank you very much.
So I would like to thank all of you who
have stayed with us to the very end. Um
this summit has been amazing in no small
part because of all of you and uh you
know it
seeing it last year I wondered if it
could possibly be better and it was and
so uh hopefully this agentic AI summit
is improving as fast as our AI models
are improving. Thank you for being here
and Don will say the final words.
>> Thank you. Thanks David. Uh again, yes,
thanks everyone for being here. I hope
that everyone really has learned a lot
uh from the summit. Uh as I mentioned uh
earlier uh this morning in my opening
remark really this has been a great
amazing journey uh with the community.
We started from the agentic air muk this
massive online course in fall 2024 and
took us uh took us all the way here with
the the first edition of Agent AI
summits last year and this year we um
you know more than doubled also in
attendees and uh changing from one day
to two extending from one day to two-day
program for the second edition of Agent
AI summit. Our goal as I mentioned um
the goal and the mission for uh Berkeley
ITI center is to steward the future of
AI for safe, secure, beneficial agentic
AI for human flourishing and we um one
of our missions is also to build open
ecosystem to really democratize and
bring the benefits of AI and agentic AI
to every individual. So that's also one
of the key motivations for this summit
is to bring everyone together. We share
knowledge. We build open ecosystem and
we hope that with this open ecosystem
and the knowledge that everyone gained
that we can together build stronger um
open ecosystem for human flourishing and
for uh building AI that really can be uh
beneficial to everyone. So with that uh
deep thanks to everyone and we hope that
you'll come back next year. Thank you
and um please do help spread the word to
your friends, your community, your
networks uh the uh the videos for all
the sessions will also be online on
YouTube. So please do help spread the
words to have your friends, your
community to uh further benefit from the
great knowledge and insights shared in
the summit. Thank you.
And we still have a a reception and a
poster session uh in the MLK building.
So hope everyone can enjoy the poster
session and the reception. Thanks
everyone.